a una grande quantità di persone.
È il vostro lavoro, è il nostro lavoro,
ma penso anche che dovremmo condividere le forze
per, diciamo,
per aiutare una migliore comprensione,
almeno dalle due parti del Mediterraneo,
che sarebbero già grandi come obiettivi.
Grazie per ciò che stai facendo e per ciò che stai scrivendo.
Thank you.
Presidente, vuole la parola?
Tocca a lei.
You don't need it now.
Ok, no, it's too much.
No, no, no.
No, first of all, I like the way you express yourself
when you say, this is very important psychologically,
the threat we are facing.
You said and you wrote in a paper.
It's important for, let's say, every kind of audience you meet
or every kind of reader you have to understand
that this is a common threat that we are facing
and there is no difference between Muslim and non-Muslim,
Christians, not Christians, whatever they are,
in, let's say, the situation they find themselves
vis-à-vis the fundamentalist kind of...
It's a threat.
It's a threat because independently of the connection,
which you rightly not even underline too much,
between fundamentalism and terrorism,
which of course exists because there is a linkage.
Terrorism finds reasons in this kind of monolithic interpretation
of the Quran, but also independently of that.
This kind of interpretation, this monolithic rigid interpretation
is something that creates a profound divide
between the societies which are prisoners
of this kind of interpretation and any other.
It is a threat for the Muslim world
because of course it is a rightly fragmented word.
You don't have a hierarchical structure
such as other religions have,
and therefore it makes sense to have different communities.
Of course, if the only interpretation of the Quran
is the ummah that has everything in itself,
the risk of not differences but conflicts is enormous
inside the Muslim world and obviously
between Muslim individuals, groups, communities,
and non-Muslim communities living close to each other
in whatever part of the world.
How can I establish a peaceful relationship with the other one
if the other one, being not a believer, is an enemy of mine?
This is crucial, not being linked by that kind,
and therefore it is a threat that we are facing.
The kind of work that you are doing,
which as Emma said is really a very precious kind of work,
is extremely useful toward the non-Muslim
just in saying and repeating, even though we are saying and repeating
that the Muslim world is not monolithic.
There are different interpretations, etc.
I don't know whether you are familiar with the Italian press
and the editorials that appear, but until a couple of years ago,
the leading newspaper of the country published editorials
in which you could read that moderate Islam does not exist,
that we would be happy to deal with,
but this is an invention of the Italian left, substantially.
Difficult to digest because so far from truth,
and therefore it makes sense also for us to have somebody giving evidence
that this is completely nonsense as I think,
but it is clear that you, I might be wrong,
are mostly speaking to Muslim readers,
somehow explaining to them that the holy text
has to be interpreted within historical contexts.
This is what is essential just to accept
that the substantial meaning of these words
does not necessarily correspond to the traditionally accepted meaning
or even to the literary meaning of these words.
This is an exercise that has been, if you want,
repeatedly accomplished in relation to the holy text of other religions,
and paradoxically it is an old exercise also for the Koran.
It's not new.
This is quite a paradox because if you are not thinking in historical terms,
you might discover that between the Koran and the Sharia
there is a difference as something completely new,
while only a thousand years ago it was already written, said and practiced.
And this too has to be somehow considered.
I wonder, something that is interesting for me is,
and it should also become a part of the exercise,
is a sort of comparative religion in the sense that other religions,
the interpretation of other holy texts,
how much they correspond to the kind of issues that you are tackling or not.
I would say that in the Christian world this kind of position,
there is one only interpretation of the holy book,
is very minoritarian, it's very limited.
You have some American minoritarian groups.
All of us know about children whose parents,
think that the only possible teaching has to be consistent
with the literary meaning of the Bible.
And therefore there is no possible school for these children
because in any other book there is something new,
that the Bible of course could not anticipate
for obvious reasons from your angle.
So really in relation to this,
the acceptance inside the Muslim world
of a literary interpretation of the Koran,
the difficult distinction between the Koran and the Shamiya,
is something that I would consider wider nowadays
than it is in the Christian world.
While the other aspects that you were highlighting
in your presentation of the fundamentalist doctrine,
namely any social and political issue has been theologized,
you said, well this is a trend that is not so minoritarian
as you could think in other religions,
because it might be due to the fact that increasingly
issues that are dealt with in the political sphere
have some sort of connection with matters of religious belief,
one reason or another I don't know,
but the fact is that issues which are being discussed
in the public sphere, in relation to which there is a position
that is considered correct from a religious angle,
these issues are, let's say, increasing in number.
And here too, it becomes also for other religions,
it is becoming increasingly important to distinguish
between the word of God and the word of the, let's say,
believers or of the hierarchy.
This is an exercise that is extremely important,
how much we owe what in Latin they call credenda
to the fact that they are immediately drawn from the words of God,
the Bible and or the Gospel,
when the credenda are something due to the hierarchy
and therefore to the Pope, to his positions,
and have these two kind of credenda the same value,
these two is an extremely important issue.
I conclusively go back to the question I was asking
Emma before.
There is a clear relationship between openness of societies
and, let's say, tolerant interpretation of religious texts
and religious credenda generally.
What comes first?
This interpretation more tolerant makes societies more open
or being a society more open,
the interpretation of holy texts is more tolerant.
It's a two-way process, I suppose.
It's difficult, so we have to imagine these as a circle
that is virtuous somehow and difficult to identify the chicken
and identify the egg in this kind of process,
but what in my view is also important is to understand the sense
of the more tolerant interpretation of religious credenda
typical of more open societies.
Does this mean that they are less religious or not?
Yesterday, in the course of the beautiful conference on Aldo Moro
in the 30th anniversary of his death,
a very serious kind of thing with panels highly qualified,
a professor of the Kennedy Government School of Harvard,
Pippa Norris, was presenting her future book on cultural convergence,
a book to be published by Oxford or Cambridge Press generally
was written three years before, as all of us know.
Therefore, she was eager to present the book a year before the publication.
Basically, by using data on practicing religious rights, etc., etc.,
she was concluding that God is for traditional and backward societies,
substantially. She didn't say so, but this was the substance of the argument.
So as soon as a society gets more modern, more open, etc.,
religiousness goes down.
I humbly objected that it is not necessarily so.
And I said, I'm not a believer, so I'm not speaking of me,
but I understand that religion becomes, in an open society,
something that is more led from inside than from religious hierarchies.
And this is part of the more openness of society.
And therefore I am convinced there are many more religious people in Italy
than those who go every Sunday to worship.
I wonder whether we can elaborate some more on these kind of issues,
because you might easily find yourself in the same position in which,
let's say, the Catholic liberals, I would call them like this,
find themselves in countries like mine or in Spain
or where there is a strong religious hierarchy.
I mean, you are saying that religion has become a sort of individual affair,
that it has been individualized as any other aspect of life,
but you are substantially speaking on behalf of an atheist society,
where...