è un termine che è linkato a Beliabon, o in Germania a amore,
che è per dire che qualcuno che crede, amora o pregge la loro allogia o la loro allogia
o l'allegio o la loro allogia a Dio o a Dio.
Questo è quello che il religioso ha significato in un momento.
Ma nel XVI-XVI secolo, il religioso è diventato un pronome abstratto,
invece di un esattivo,
e ha iniziato a riferire a un sistema intero di pratiche
che contengono una comunità, non solo quella,
ma una comunità che ha un set di doctrini coerenti
e che ha una struttura istituzionale.
E il religioso,
quindi, invece di il religioso essere una proprietà di uomini o di gruppi di uomini,
i uomini erano una proprietà di religioso.
I uomini iniziarono a sopravviare alla religiosa.
E penso che questo sia stato, in un senso,
invece di sopravviare a Dio o a Dio,
o avere alcune relazioni con Dio o Dio,
le persone iniziarono a vedere in relazione a questa comunità
istituzionale e strutturata.
E puoi capire come l'uomo iniziò a cambiare
e questa idea di identità,
che è un'identità categorica,
che è un'identità strutturata,
iniziava ad essere nata.
E penso che dobbiamo tornare a questo periodo moderno
in modo da capire
dove,
la roots di alcuni di questi problemi
sono.
Poi immaginiamo
cosa succederà
se, per esempio,
le persone che
imparano molto da
Hume, Locke, Berkley, Kant, Hegel, Marx, Spinoza,
inizieranno a chiamarsi
Hume, Locke, Kant, Hegel,
e
se inizieranno a pensare a loro
come una comunità e un'associazione strutturata
di Kant, che crede solo a Kant e a nessuno altro,
la kind of intellectual disagreement
che vediamo nella filosofia
tornerà a majori conflitti ideologici e politici
e magari i filosofi saranno ancora violenti
ad uno l'altro, chi lo sa.
Ma,
penso che questo
intero sistema deve essere
smantellato.
E l'altra cosa, ovviamente, la distinzione musicale che ho detto,
questo è qualcosa che,
se lo introdurete in questa notione di religione,
la distinzione musicale
racconta la distinzione
tra la vera religione
e la falsa religione.
L'idea che,
non è solo l'idea che c'è solo un Dio,
che è qualcosa che è comune
a molte, molte religioni,
non solo a certe religioni,
ma l'idea che c'è
un vero Dio
e tutti gli altri Dio sono falsi
e, per questo,
dovrebbero essere esclusi
o hanno
un'idea esclusiva
a un Dio,
invece di tutti gli altri falsi Dio.
Penso che sia anche
un'idea che ha
giocato il havoc.
Se lo guardate,
siamo qui
parlando del pluralismo,
ma questo è un monismo esclusivo.
Penso che
abbia
un'impatto
molto dimenticato
sul modo in cui
le persone si rilassano.
Quindi,
l'idea che
la religione è una cosa,
devi scegliere una religione
all'esclusione di ogni altra religione,
che è
introdotta nel discorso
da una distinzione musicale.
Penso che questo sia
una cosa che dobbiamo domandare
e scegliere.
Volevo solo
mettere su la tavola
questa molto veloce
radicalizzazione
di
la fiducia e delle identità
che si sono fatti nel XV-XVI secolo,
che continua ad avere un impatto
su noi oggi
e che è
ora totalmente globale.
Non c'è una sola
persona
che si chiama
religione
nella maggior parte del mondo
che non pensa
nella sua o la sua religione in questo modo.
Penso che sia il momento
che, intellettualmente, la prendiamo seriamente
e iniziamo a scegliere.
Thank you.
Sebastiano.
Before I start, let me thank
Rosette Dialogue of Civilization.
I'm informed of the project
since the beginning and I always thought it was great
but I can say it's still better
also because it's a beautiful day
in this fantastic foundation, of course.
But I think it's very important that we discuss
these things among us and
try to understand as much as we can
on such a difficult and complex subject.
I mean, today we are
supposed to speak about
global challenges
for politics
within the framework of the radicalization
of identity. The first thing I note
is that
usually we think of global changes
in very different terms.
Global changes usually derive
from more or less universal
problems confronted with
local institution.
For instance,
take environment.
You cannot solve
problems of environment in one country.
You need to expand them
more or less universally.
That's why you have
a global challenge
because the problem is global.
The institutions you have are not global.
They are local and you cannot solve the problem
given this gap.
So the same can be
said for finance.
You need regulation. This regulation cannot be
only local. They must be
general. And there are
not such institutions
that can do that.
So the structure of global challenging
for politics usually is
global problems
too much local
institutions. Instead when we speak
of radical identities, perhaps
we have an opposite problem.
Institutional is too large, too big,
too comprehensive
and we need something more specific,
more local.
And so we have
a kind of reversion.
The problem is the other way round.
Instead of having global
problems and local institutions, we have
local problems and institutions that
are too large.
How to confront ourselves with
such kind of problems?
Within political philosophy,
am I not so radical?
I think of myself as a moderate
Kantian, so Rajiv don't worry,
we will not be too dangerous.
There are two main solutions I see.
One is Kimlik as
liberal multiculturalism.
As Vivorca said before,
is not exactly popular in this moment
among political persons, but still
is an intriguing offer.
There is one basic
problem in the idea,
I mean there are many, but one I think is
particularly evident and strong, that
this kind of formula presupposes
a peaceful world.
Whereas, as was said
before,
identity problem
begin, as Achille said before,
are connected
almost always with hard times.
They are caused by violence,
by offence.
I mean, as Martin
Hassen has written, we have many
identities. When radical
identity comes out, it's because
these many identities,
at least part of them, are offended
and humiliated. That's why
we...
And this means that
liberal multiculturalism is very difficult
because you assume
a peaceful world, whereas
radicalization of identity
comes out in a very
hard world.
The second
model we have in political philosophy
is probably post-colonialism,
which is more
a bunch of different doctrines,
but still as a kind of
found soul.
I think that
post-colonialists have different problems.
It's more apt
to our times, but
and I think
it's a problem between the first level and the second
level. The first level being the level
of the object of
post-colonialism, mainly what Achille calls
epistemic injustice.
On this side, I think post-colonialism
is quite right. There has been an
epistemic injustice and we should
do something to understand each other,
to not offend people continuing
with the epistemic injustice.
But I think
post-colonialism has an enormous problem
with the second level argument,
which usually
comes from post-modernism.
This second Archimedean
argument is an argument
based on profound skepticism
or reason. And I think that
the second level argument,
the meta-argument, cancels the
possibility of the object
of post-colonialism. So it's
basically both models don't
work. Of course I
reduced my criticism to a few words, but
it's what is possible in this short
time. So I
think we could work toward
another model, which is
a
version of the Kimlisca model,
but I think more modest in some
way. It's not probably multiculturalism,
it's not
probably liberal multiculturalism,
but what I call multicultural liberalism.
It's not just
for joking, it's not just
a pun, but I think
that the core of multicultural liberalism
is constitutional pluralism.
And this is
the basis