sub-time shock and the recovery of world economy and science and technology should play a role.
And I said there should be no time for nationalism, for Japanese strategy.
We should really open up. This is a great moment for Japan to design post catch-up world model
with more openness to the world and hence I said there is no time for nationalism.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Another window of hope with the no nationalism is the tsunami and thank you for the inauguration of the new term science diplomacy.
There is no better place to start with that.
Now, Professor Pradeep, President Pradeep will deliver a speech on Japan's role within and beyond the crisis.
Being the last, it's lucky and unlucky at the same time. You may also draw some conclusion, Professor Pradeep.
This was I'm asking for. I don't know if I'm able to do it, you know.
But first of all I have really to thank the Japanese ambassador, Mr. Kono, because he invited me
and with Osservatorio Asia organized this meeting that I have found very, very fruitful.
And we have also to, we have the responsibility to take the consequence of the teaching that we had today.
Now I am trying to sum up, to draw some conclusion of what we listened today
and to make some comparison between the European and Italian situation, the Japanese one.
First of all we had a comparison between the twin deficit, Italian and Japanese, very, very useful.
But with a remarkable difference that gives you the idea in which crisis we live.
First of all, in absolute and relative terms, the Japanese deficit is much higher than the Italian.
But as you have listened, 95% is owned by Japanese. And so it's not under attack.
There is a big difference. There is the possibility of having, taking the political decision that you listed before, increasing taxation.
So I don't know if it will be possible to take that because you can tell this because you are not running for elections,
because otherwise it will be difficult to announce this increase in taxation as you announced before.
But in any case, being independent from the big financial world, you have time to decide and to handle your policy.
This is a lesson for Italy and for all people who really push it for the globalization of financial markets.
Let's say the sense of avoiding risk that being in a big financial market gives, this is absolutely not true.
We have Italy is in risk in the sense that I don't think that is a real risk.
But anyway, it's close to the risk, is reputed to the financial market for the risk only because our debt is not owned by Italians.
And this is a reflection that we have to do.
Second general reflection, a question mark also.
It's quite interesting that you complained about the increase of the yen and the problem that is given.
And it's very interesting because in this strange world you always lose the sovereignty on the rate of exchange.
Even if you are inside the euro or if you are not inside the euro, when there are behavior of the big players in the financial market like we have now,
it's difficult that you can manage your rate of exchange in the most convenient way for your initial policy.
I think that this is a general lesson that we have to learn by your teaching today.
Well, I have also been happy because of your statistics.
The primary surplus was the best behavior was under my government.
We were not in agreement before, but I'd be happy to read that.
But you posed a strong question.
Why the ring fence has not been applied to Greece by Europe?
But look, there is no rational answer.
It's only a political answer because when Greece started to shake, it was enough to have 30 billion euros to stop it.
Now 10 times more is not sufficient.
And so it's difficult that I answer your question in a rational way.
Simply, we have a Europe that is half-cooked and the supernatural powers are not sufficient to take decisions in this difficult environment.
And so the decision has been taken by the national government, mainly in this case by Germany.
And the electorate was not eager to help countries in need.
There was a political situation that made this difficult.
And still now, you see, the European policy is going in the right direction.
But because of the behavior of the electorate is slow and insufficient in quantity.
Right direction, but slow, you know.
The aid to Greece, it comes always late and always insufficient.
So the international market, they never say, OK, we understand that there is a ring fence, as you ask.
And they try again and try again and try again.
But this is politics, you know.
When we started the euro, I do remember the dialogue with the Chancellor of Corsica.
Because, you know, I was president of the Commission and I raised the problem of, look, we have a common currency, we need a common taxation.
Ring fence.
And the answer was wise from the political point of view.
The answer was, look, we did such a big effort in building up the euro.
It was so difficult to stop with the Deutsche Mark that now, please, we should do it later.
But then we had a period of change in which Italians or Germans were afraid about globalization,
were afraid about Chinese competition, were afraid about immigration, were afraid about everything.
And so the decision of the ring fence has not been organized.
This is the situation of Europe.
But I am not surprised because Europe has always developed through crisis.
If you look at the history of Europe, and then, you know, it's a fantastic challenge.
It's a fantastic challenge.
We shall go on another 50 years to complete it, you know, or maybe more.
But this is, we have no options.
So this is why I am also sure that the euro will not collapse, you know, because there is no interest of any European country to do it, you know.
The German surface is unbelievable.
The real China in the world is Germany, it's not China, you know.
And so we shall have all this problem of waving, but no disruption of the euro will be because there is not interest of anybody.
Then you raise the big change in population and, you know, demography matters.
I think that if you are wise, demography matters a little less than we fear, in the sense that, you know,
the average age increases, but the health of people is not the same than the generation before.
So clearly you have to move the pension system and to have to adapt the health system.
But a human being 50 years ago, being 50 years old is not a human being of today being 50 years old.
And so we have not to be so mathematical, you know, to describe this.
Of course we have to adapt the system, but this, I tell you that from this point of view, Italy is absolutely in a perfect situation, you know.
With the last reforms for 30 years we shall not have any imbalance and any major increase in the pension costs, you know.
And it was painful, it was difficult, but this has been done, you know.
There is a difference, clearly, between Japan and Europe, is immigration, you know.
You have shown that to take care of old people you have robots.
We have women coming from East Europe called badanti.
There is a big difference. The robots have no children.
The women coming from East Europe, they may have children, you know.
And so they may change demography and the robots cannot change demography.
And this is something that is very, very important and it makes Japan different from other countries.
Of course you fall into the cultural problem raised by Professor Maffei, you know, because he really stresses the uniqueness of Japan in history, you know.
And with immigration you lose this uniqueness, but is it an advantage or a disadvantage?
This is another problem, you know.
We have no choice because our immigrants come in any case and so we have no political choice.
But you have a choice, but it is a choice, you know.
And I think that this will influence heavily, can influence heavily the problem of aging of Japan, of any country.
But anyway, we also understood the other great difference, how big is your effort on innovation?
And this makes a great difference in favor of Japan, you know.
If you perform this plan in spite of the public deficit, putting a lot of money on innovation, I think that you are in the right track.
And this is a difference with Italy.
We have decreased our R&D expenditure that was already low enough because of financial constraints.
But here we are in a completely different strategy.
In this case I do back the Japanese strategy, not the Italian one.
In immigration is the reverse, but anyway this is my personal opinion, you know.
And your policy on innovation will be the real asset of Japan.
But taking another short observation, the Japanese history in the recent time has been very unique because you have been leading for one generation at least.
And the world model was Japan and in the end of the 80s there was this change, you know.
The book of Morita Akio on Japan was able to say no, how was it taken in the United States, you know.
And then the stagnation came, or the slow growth came, and clearly it is difficult to explain.
Because all the phenomena that you explained, aging and so on, they are much slower than the change of the direction of Japanese policy.
So I do think that political mistakes also were done, or not adequate evaluation of the changing of the world, you know.
The bubble of the 90s was certainly a mistake, a political mistake in my opinion, you know.
Now I have no other figures to analyze it, but clearly looking with a historical perspective this was the moment of the Japanese switch.
But this is very understood and I don't want to stop it, but I want to stress one evolution that I think is important.
Japan, in spite of the slow growth or accompanying the growth or allowing the growth, the slow growth rate, has exported a lot of manufacturing during this period of stagnation.
And you have become a big manufacturer abroad, with two consequences, having then a positive flow of income from your investment abroad, but even more opening new links.
And the new links are Asian links, not American or European links.
So I found Japan today very different from Japan yesterday, and my observation is that now Japan is an Asian country.
In the sense that if you look at trade, if you look at cross investment, China is your biggest importer, number one, and it was absolutely unbelievable, unbelievable in the recent past.
And then I think that these links have become more and stronger and stronger and stronger and stronger.
I give you an example.
One year ago when you had the terrible tsunami, the consequence was to stop an unbelievable number of Chinese factories.
You know, for months and months, why? Because the high-tech supplies went from Japan, and the links is also the reverse.
In the flood of Thailand, a lot of Japanese suppliers suffered because they had no more the market for them.
And without any deliberate policy, but because of the growth of Asia, you will become more and more Asian.
And I think that this will have also an enormous political consequence.
I'm only guessing, but when you are linked in a new economic environment, step by step you go also into a different political environment, you know.
And after the centuries of isolation that you explained, after they link with Germany, with the major revolution, and the United States in the after world period,
I think that is starting a period in which you must deploy a strong inter-Asian link because this is the market, this is the link,
this is the challenge that Japan has now.
Clearly this brings a challenge in relation with Europe because I think that you need Europe to counterbalance this change of history.
And we need Japan for the same sake, you know.
But if you analyze the summits, the meeting between the European Union and Japan, we discuss very interesting things, you know, non-tariff barriers and so on.
But there is no sense of history in the sense that there is no deep thought on these long-term events, how to, let's say, adapt our relation to this new history that is, in my opinion, is absolutely impossible to avoid, you know.
And this, I think, will be the challenge that we have as Italy today here, as Europe tomorrow in Brussels, I don't know.
But to understand that this change in real things must make us thinking to the political future with more freedom than we have now, you know, because we cannot, let's say, restrict the problems between Europe and Japan to the non-tariff barriers, you know.
Well, of course they are important, you know, but there is something more.
There is how to build a future together or, you know, to take the consequence of being separate, you know.
This is last small observation is concerning the Japanese, it's more a question than, of course, an opinion because I am not a specialist on Japan, you know, but I have been taken by the Japanese behavior after the tsunami.
Because it's a counter that, from the economic point of view, I am an economist, you know, has demonstrated to have a resilience and the ability to change that is fantastic, you know, but also an absolute new challenge, you know.
I did remember two years ago, you are more able to define the precise date, the Japanese government made the message, we shall arrive to 50% of nuclear energy from 3035, you know.
Let's say new strategy, nuclear. Then you have a terrible accident, a complete change of mind, a new political debate and now the necessity of a new policy.
And this, as far as I know, will be decided by you and your minister in the next month, but now what is absolutely remarkable is how Japan has adapted to the lack of energy.
You know, distributing, decreasing consumption, distributing it during the week, night, day, adapting, and so has been able in a few months to make factories resurrect and the production, let's say, not to be normalized, but almost normalized, you know.
But the long-term changes are there, you know. Japan will spend at least 35 billion euros more on energy import now.
Then I don't know which policy will be adopted, you know, but if the nuclear power station remains closed, as they are now all but two and they will be all closed in a few months, if this goes on, you have to spend it immediately because you need time to implement the alternative energy project.
So this is, in my opinion, a very, very, very difficult time.
But to sum up all this today, the real new fact that there is a big new supply chain in the world that we cannot call it Japanese, we cannot call it Chinese, we must call it Asian.
And this is the change of the world. So deep that two weeks ago, when the managers of Apple, they came to President Obama to present a new strategy, you know, and they told that they will robotize the Fox Coalitions.
Of course, the answer of the President was, look, now the added value, the labor added value in the iPad and the iPhone is almost negligible, let's say.
$70 for iPad or $20 and $10 for iPhone, you know, and then if you robotize, it will decrease more and more and we will arrive to two, three percent of the value of the product.
So why you don't bring the production to California? And the answer was because now the supply chain, the Asia supply chain is absolutely unique in the world.
And it's not a problem of cost. The quick response to the change, the organization, let's say the intermediate skilled organizers of the labor, they are now a resource that we find only in Asia.
And this is, in my opinion, what is happening, that clearly Japan must take the consequence of this change. And because of scientific level, because of your knowledge of your organization, you must exploit this happening.
Inside the new reality.
E, ovviamente, nella luce di questo cambiamento, noi europei e gli americani, di loro,
dobbiamo completamente cambiare la strategia che abbiamo tra noi.
Queste sono le mie reflezioni, e vi ringrazio per la lezione che avete dato a noi.
Grazie al professor Prodi, sembra che la globalizzazione sia l'epitome di complessità.
Ora, prima di che la santa vada completamente giù, abbiamo un po' di minuti per qualche domanda che potete avere.
Quindi, se c'è un'altra domanda, riuscite a riscaldare la sua o la sua mano e posate la domanda, se potete.
Sì.
Potete provare a parlare?
A svegliare?
Sì, venite qui. Venite qui.
Grazie molto. Sono un giornalista, e ora voglio chiedere un'altra domanda.
Il professor Prodi ha detto che l'azione reale, l'Asia, è il nuovo fattore della politica mondiale.
Ho la stessa opinione, sono stato per molti anni in Giappone come giornalista,
e ho trovato questo molto interessante.
Ma per Giappone questo pose una grande domanda, perché la priorità dei Stati Uniti,
la relazione con Giappone, forse deve cambiare.
E quindi, questo è un problema molto grande, non solo per Giappone, ma anche per l'Europa.
E vorrei sapere l'opinione della gente giapponese su questo grande problema,
perché questa strida relazione tra Giappone e gli Stati Uniti
ha in qualche modo evitato a Giappone di giocare un ruolo molto grande nell'Asia.
Ma questo ruolo è inevitabile, quindi vorrei avere la vostra opinione su questo.
Sì, non è facile, ma prima di tutto, per rispondere a questa domanda,
bisogna pensare sulla strategia americana nel posto Pacifico.
E ci sono molte contraddizioni, anche su questo, perché in teoria,
gli americani vogliono isolare la Cina.
President Obama visita tutti i paesi in Cina, non Cina,
e la Missa Clinton fa lo stesso.
E, diciamo, nel ritorno alla campagna dell'elezione,
la Cina sarà un'assetta.
Ma è come la situazione europea sull'euro.
La comunità di negozio non vuole nemmeno avere questo comportamento.
Quindi parlano alto, ma l'azione non è così forte.
Quindi penso che, perché questo, c'è molto ruolo di manovra per Giappone.
C'è molta libertà in questo senso.
Non viviamo nella situazione del 20-25 anni fa.
Gli Stati Uniti hanno un grande potere, ma il più grande potere del mondo,
è che non possono agire solo.
E quindi, da questo punto di vista,
Giappone, ovviamente, rimane un amico forte e loyale dei Stati Uniti,
ma ha molto ruolo di manovra che Giappone non aveva prima.
Ma perché questa è la nuova politica del mondo, è la stessa cosa per l'Europa,
non la usiamo perché siamo divisi,
ma il ruolo di manovra per l'Europa
potrebbe essere molto, molto più alto che il ruolo che esploitiamo ora.
Abbiamo spazio, il professor Onida.
Una domanda al professor Ito.
Prendendo il risultato del 95% dei salari giapponesi
che sono stati ai salari giapponesi,
a causa dell'integrazione dei mercati finanziari,
cosa evita i salari giapponesi di diversificare un po' il loro portogiovole?
Per esempio, per sostituire alcuni dei bondi a lungo termine da Giappone,
che sovraggono, credo, 2%,
magari con alcuni bondi italiani a lungo termine da Giappone,
che sovraggono 5%.
I salari giapponesi hanno provato i bondi a lungo termine da Giappone,
come i bondi australiani, i bondi di New Zealand,
e sono stati toccati, perché i bondi sono apprezzati,
e la diprezzazione principale è stata molto più che una differenzione di interesse.
Quindi sono diventati molto bianchi del rischio di currency.
E questo è stato pagato in una crisi finanziaria mondiale.
Gli istituti finanziari giapponesi sono stati toccati in strutture
che le istituzioni finanziarie dell'U.S. sono stati a pressione
e le istituzioni finanziarie europee sono stati a porto.
Quindi è stato rinforzato che essere a casa sia sicuro.
Questo è il sentimento dei loro istituti giapponesi.
I stock giapponesi sono underperformati.
Hanno perso un quarto dei valori da una crisi finanziaria mondiale.
Per esempio, quando i prezzi sono sbagliati,
la risposta reale è alta.
Quindi la risposta del 1% dei bondi giapponesi
sembra essere una risposta molto buona.
Questa è la conclusione dei saveri giapponesi e dei saveri corporati.
I saveri giapponesi sono anche spingiti.
Quindi i paesi giapponesi e i portofogli corporati
sono sbagliati dai bondi giapponesi.
Come ho detto, il 95% sono sbagliati dai bondi giapponesi,
ma quando i bondi giapponesi sono sbagliati in due anni,
sono sbagliati dai bondi giapponesi.
Quindi chi paga? Le corporazioni giapponesi.
Le corporazioni giapponesi si rinvolgono ai loro salari
e sono sbagliati dai bondi giapponesi.
Quindi l'incendio del net viene da saveri corporati.
Ma perché le corporazioni si rinvolgono ai loro salari?
Per il momento si deve aspettare a investire.
Quando gli investimenti corporati si rinvolgono,
è il momento in cui i bondi giapponesi vengono in crisi.
E anche le corporazioni continuano a salare,
ma c'è un limite che possono salire.
Poi, dopo 10-15 anni,
anche quando si raccogliano i salari corporati,
tutti i salari sono sbagliati dai bondi giapponesi.
E' un posto molto strano, non c'è un net.
Tutti i salari privati sono i libri del governo giappone.
Quindi il governo giappone deve tornare a salare
molto velocemente, in 2-5 anni.
Grazie.
In ogni caso, non c'è speranza di investire in bondi italiani.
La ultima domanda.
Io vorrei chiedere alla professora Matsui una domanda.
Grazie.
Nella vostra parola,
hai detto che i giapponesi hanno un bonde molto forte
che li colla insieme.
E hai parlato del comunitarismo.
Come si chiama il comunitarismo?
Sì, sono sicura.
Ok.
Nella vostra parola, hai parlato del comunitarismo.
E io sono sicura con questa idea,
ma non pensi che questa meraviglia del giappone
possa anche tornare ad un obstacolo,
ad un indirizzo,
quando si tratta di cambiamenti di politiche.
Io stavo pensando sul problema del nucleo,
e quando si tratta di creare nuove decisioni.
Quindi il paese giapponese,
il impredicabile,
non può anche tornare ad un paese di cambiamenti.
Quindi non può essere che questo comunitarismo
possa anche tornare ad un obstacolo
per il reverse del paese giapponese?
Grazie.
Sì, stavo pensando se il comunitarismo
non poteva essere un obstacolo
per creare nuove decisioni.
Grazie.
Per capire le specifiche uniche del giappone,
io uso un metodo particolare, comparativo.
Questo metodo è basato su variabili di cross-culture,
con due parti.
Una parte, per esempio, il comunitarismo,
e l'altra parte, l'individualismo.
Quindi, ovviamente, la tradizione occidentale
favorisce l'individualismo.
Il giapponese, nel Giappone,
è molto forte il comunitarismo,
come la Cina, ovviamente,
perché questo è comitato a tutte le persone dell'Este Asia.
Ma nel Giappone, il comunitarismo
è molto forte, perché ci sono alcune connotazioni.
I giapponesi hanno quello che io chiamo
il secondo sindrome,
il sindrome che ha tentato i giapponesi
di continuare l'improvemento,
e, ovviamente, l'indice alto di evitare l'incertezza.
Tutti questi elementi, insieme,
rendono i giapponesi molto diversi
tra altri paesi del mondo scenico dell'Este Asia.
E penso che questo punto molto forte del Giappone
ora è questo etos specifico.
E sono sicuro che il Giappone
sarà in grado di, ancora una volta,
affrontare proprio questo nuovo tipo di sfida.
Questo nuovo tipo di sfida per il Giappone
è molto importante, perché
i giapponesi devono cambiare il loro etos.
Per ora, il Giappone era un paese piccolo,
ora il Giappone deve usare,
come ho chiamato prima,
la gialla gialla giacca della globalizzazione.
In altri termini, il Giappone deve cambiare
una delle caratteristiche più importanti,
la comunità.