question.
Thank you for the invitation, I'm very happy to be here and happy that this is a conversation
not a speech, you know, sermons, we have enough sermons, you know.
Your question, you know, there is a proverbio calabrese, calabrese say that in Italian is
si peccora si fa, il lupo se lo mangia.
If you are a sheep the wolf eats you, you know, if you pretend to be a sheep.
This is Europe now, you know, it's a, we have, there is no, the courage to be Europe, but
there is the clear understanding that the single countries they cannot play a game in
the world and so we are in between the two choices and when you are between two choices
in the middle of the river you have no choice and, you know, when I travel around the world
everybody ask me, well, you are the first trader, if I go to Middle East, to Israel,
to Palestine, you are the first trader, you know us so well and you don't count anything,
you are not existent simply because we have made the first step for the Union but then
the decision making process has stopped.
So it's not a problem of having too much Europe but having too little Europe in my opinion,
you know, and when you are in this situation you have against you your supporter and your
enemies because nobody is happy for the situation and we are in this uneasy situation so we
can get out only starting back to take decisions.
If we start again to take decisions we are out of this messy situation, otherwise we
shall be for a long time in, first of all the campaign is different, not that there
is an enthusiasm for voting, you know, you don't say debates, you know, but when there
is a debate on that it's not anymore on internal policy only as it was in the past, European
elections have always been national elections, this time even if there is no, let's say,
enthusiasm or common very diffuse debate but when there is a discussion is on European
issues because for the first time there is a wide diffuse opinion against Europe, you
know, and this from one side is the consequence of let's say a crisis but from the other
side the first time that we are in front of a very strong decision.
Coming to the details of that clearly is a progress that you have candidates, you never
had candidates in the past, you know, when I was appointed president of the commission
it was a crisis but I never had, you know, tackled any political battle, I had no idea
to be president of the commission, simply the head of states they decided to ask me
to be a commission.
Now you have a battle probably with Schultz, well probably between Schultz and the Luxembourg
prime minister and they are members of two different parties, they have very similar
platforms but anyway two platforms and the first time that you have to decide between
concrete faces, concrete, you know, so this is a progress, a very important progress,
of course even in this case it's half of the bread is half baked because clearly you should
need to have a direct election of the two candidates, you know, to have the real battle
and the European institution will be popular when we shall vote directly for a German
socialist or a French popular or an Italian so on and so on and so on but now is already
some progress in the right direction.
What will happen, you know, because of that, probably which will be the outcome, nobody
knows because before the election we don't know the results but if you look at the opinion
polls only big coalitions will be able to run Europe, I repeat following the opinion polls
because you have such a number of anti-European votes in which an alliance between
Christian democratic popular and liberals or socialist and liberal will not probably
be enough to have a coalition so you will have a parliament split between pro-European
and anti-European and the pro-European will be pushed to be more and more pro-European
because of the dynamics of the new dynamics of the parliament.
Clearly there is also a danger that is not written in any newspaper, I never read about
it, that in the European parliament you never have Philip Boostering, you know, we have
a discipline and then we have rules that to have Philip Boostering or, you know, you need
to represent a shade of the parliament and a number of seven states of the parliament,
probably in this parliament for the first time you will have the possibility of Philip
Boostering and so we probably shall assist to very complicated debates but apart from
that, that is important, you know.
Just a quick follow up, is it conceivable to you that the European Council will not
follow the results of the election and choose a different candidate than the ones that are
now competing?
Possible, yes, possible because till now in the last years the council has been dominating
vis-à-vis the commission.
We had the reverse in the European power, you know, and so it's possible but I do think
because the difference between the two candidates are not so radical, so deep that probably
even in the council you will have an agreement.
What will happen that, you know, now the polls are socialist centre-left and centre-right
very almost equal, you know, so in theory if the popular win, the Juncker will be the
candidate, if the centre-left wins, let's say Schulz will be the candidate for the commission
but I know very well my friend Juncker and I think that he will prefer a less tiring
job, you know, and so also he has been prime minister so many years, he has his colleagues,
I think that maybe will be more comfortable to be president of the council, you know,
and so you could have this type of agreement, you know, that is not so bad, you know, because
everybody chooses his own, let's say, life scheme, you know, but I don't see a clash
between council and parliament because council and parliament because...
Professore, if there is no clash between the council and parliament and I think you're
right, I think it will be a grand coalition, isn't there a danger then that that grand
coalition will not deliver anything other than the policies that we now have? In other
words, Europeans will vote for someone either of the centre-left or right but we end up
with the same policies, is that a danger from this?
Well, in life suicide is always an option, you know, so it's how can I ask, I can answer
now, maybe, I think that in my experience Europe has taken a decision when it was close
to the brink, you know, close to the crisis and in this moment I do think that...
Well, let us, I want to clarify my forecast, you know, not to escape your question.
I don't think that there will be immediate change. I think that there will be still
some sort of waving but with more systemic progress, you know, slow but in the right
direction. Also because, you know, you have a campaign, well, the campaign is always different
from the election but if you follow the campaign Schultz is strongly committed to progress,
you know, much more than the other Germans and so the compromise will be a progress
not so quick, not so, let's say, revolutionary but some progress and this is what I think
because clearly there is also another problem in that even in this there was no meditation
of that, you know. You asked me about anti-European, you know, but there is one country in which
there is no danger of anti-European vote. It's Germany. It's Germany, the party for Germany
that has been backed by a lot of strong people starting from the previous CEO of IBM Germany
and then President of German Federation of Industry, German Confindustrie, we should
say, Henkel, Mr. Henkel. They got 3.9% of the votes only, you know, and, you know, why
was that? Well, this is my opinion, you know, because in Germany the Chancellor with the
severe policy has, let's say, has been able to forbid the rising of addressing. First
of all, I have to tell you clearly what I think about Ukraine, you know, what I was
thinking in the long run. Why in the large went we did it easily with Poland, with Baltic
countries and not with Ukraine? Because Ukraine is different. Ukraine is neither European
nor Russian. The future of Ukraine, of a united Ukraine, I mean, if you split it, but I think
would be disaster, but of a united Ukraine is only if Ukraine is a bridge between European
Union and Russia. There is no other option. I met Putin five days before the deep crisis
when he came to Rome in November. We discussed, you know, strongly talk about that, you know,
and I expressed the same words, you know, that is Ukraine cannot be Russian, but cannot
also be European, you know. Why things developed in this way? Simply because you remember
that was supposed to have a summit in Vilnius in the 26th of November of, let's say, around
26th of November, and the common forecast was European package and then some sort of,
let's say, European choice. It is called moderate European choice. Well, I told my opinion
was that, and it is still now, even if now is so difficult, that there is no incompatibility
between the Russian custom union with Russia, Kazakhstan and Belarus, and the agreement
with the European Union. Of course, you need some adaptation, but only technical adaptation.
There is nothing theological that forbids to have both. And my position, and I wrote also
an article in the New York Times on that, is that we had to make any effort to get this type
of agreement. And then, clearly, Putin was in the mood to exploit any occasion, and the Europeans
have given him the occasion to do it. Let's say the offer was full of IMF type conditions,
and then Putin came with the money here, good or bad money, I don't know, but anyway,
with a clear offer, and from one side he twisted the arm, and from the other side he offered,
let's say, some immediate relief to a very, very indebted country. So from one side you had
an actor able to do it immediately, to change the rules of the game, and from the other side
it complicated. You cannot have foreign policy with unanimity of 28 states. It's so clear.
It's not possible. So you give up to the idea to have a foreign policy with the rules you have now.
And in Ukraine it was normal, which is the result. But now the Ukrainian case is a game between
United States and Russia. But why United States and Ukraine? Tell me one reason should be Canada,
because they have so many Ukrainian immigrants, but United States they have no relations,
simply because Europe was unable to elaborate a policy. This is my clear opinion about the Ukrainian case.
And this is the reason why the last decision I have taken in my government has been to say no
to the Bush with other European countries. Of course I didn't do it alone, you know.
But I said no to have Ukraine and Georgia as members of NATO, because in my idea why I do think
that all the former Yugoslavian countries are by definition members of the European Union
will be today or tomorrow. The Ukrainian case is different, because the nature, the ethnic,
historical make of Ukraine a mixed country. Don't forget that Kiev has been the cradle of the
Orthodox Church and all that. This is history. So you have to play wisely if you want to have
a result you have to play a wise game.
So given all of the weakness and problems facing a European foreign policy, what do you think Europe
should now do to de-escalate this conflict and also secure some, how can Ukraine be secured as a state?
Because obviously it's very bad for Europe if there's a very unstable state on its borders.
And the US is interested, but the US is also interested and in fact probably more interested
in what's happening in the South China Sea in the longer term. So where does Europe go now?
Well in the longer term I simply think that, and it was also a debate of the last days,
if you have a defense policy as you have now in Europe, simply this is not an option,
because you will not have any possibility of let's say real military policy or so.
This is the reason why the United States are the players in the game, simply because there is no way
of Europeans to be actors. You imagine, look, for the Libyan War, well I'm so blunt,
but in case of the Libyan War, without the American help, even the British and the French together
couldn't win the Libyan resistance. There was a moment in which there were even no ammunition
to perform the job, even if it was not a direct American engagement.
And this is the European, and Putin knows very well which is the European situation.
This is why I'm telling you that we have to complete the European process.
This means foreign and military policy. I admit that it will be the last decision to be taken,
but you have to go in this direction if you want to have a role in the world.
Look, in the last, well we have a conversation, so we have to go to the end of it,
but when we have the situation we have now, different policy, a big leading counter of Europe,
that simply they decided to have a referendum whether to be a member of the Union or not,
which is the impression from outside.
Not just a civilian power which has been its article of faith, but should be a military power.
And the other thing I hear you say, that we should reach some kind of decisive resolution
to the so-called UK problem, and are you hinting they should be out?
No, I don't vote. They decided to vote, not me. I'm angry because they decided to have a referendum,
not because they are out. They have to decide, simply.
When you say we should have a referendum, yes or no, you put a question mark.
This is what I am simply telling. On the civilian Europe, I don't say that we have to spend like United States
in terms of defense and so on, but our, let's say, defensive capacity now is one-tenth
of what could be with the same budget being together. I'm simply putting that, you know.
We are like the Belgian Army in the First World War, that the soldiers did not understand French
and they were not knowing what to do in the battle. We are in the situation in which there is no coordination.
And look, remember that we did step back because in 1999, maybe I am wrong,
but the Saint-Malo agreement between France and the UK was to unite forces as Saint-Malo.
And then nothing has been done, so I am not preaching the revolution simply to do what was decided to be done,
simply like that. And we don't consider the soft power we are losing.
Let us put apart the military power, but the soft power we are losing.
When I was president of the European Commission, it was a few years ago, but not one century ago.
You know, we had the annual meeting with the Chinese president, European Union and China meeting,
and it was very interesting because we go to this meeting with a dossier like that,
in which everything that is butter, marmalade, customs and so on, visa and passports.
And the Chinese president was absolutely not interested in anything about that.
He simply was asking me about the euro, only like that.
Really, you will have one currency only, really you will drop the French franc and the Deutsche mark.
He didn't ask me about the lira, but anyway, this probably was in the moment of...
And this was, I think, but really you will have a piece of paper like that, yes.
Then in the last meeting before the euro, obsession was, can we have the euro in our reserves?
I said, yes, of course, you know, and they start to buy the euro.
And I do remember the meeting after the euro, you remember that the euro value was down compared to the dollar.
And so I was a little ashamed, you know, to go there.
You imagine, he told me, look, President, you have given me a very bad advice,
but I shall go on buying euros for two reasons.
First of all, because the euro will go up.
And it was right.
But the second is more interesting, because I don't want to live in a world in which there is only one in command.
And if there is a euro side by side with the dollar, there will be also room for China.
Examine the Chinese policy about the currency in the last two years.
The euro does not exist.
They are up to 25% of their reserves.
That's fine, you know.
In the last two years, they are simply working on having the ring being the one, up and up in exchange.
They are simply preparing the exchange will be a long way, you know,
but they are speeding up and it's very interesting, you know.
China is fascinated by the United States, you know, even in welfare state.
I don't know why a communist country can be fascinated by American welfare state, but this is another point.
But in the monetary policy, they have chosen London.
And I think that this is also a political decision, you know,
in the sense that they will have a strong power also inside Europe, you know.
And clearly it's an enormous change in terms of soft power that we have lost in this period of time, you know.
And I think that Europe has an enormous soft power, you know,
because of history of civilization, of different culture, different language, different, you know.
And because of the political division, we are not using it.
Bridget.
Professore, you've done a lot of work in Africa over the last number of years.
And Africa was a very major focus of EU foreign policy in terms of development and cooperation.
And of course China is also now very interested in Africa.
So how do you see Europe's relations with Africa developing?
And what is your experience of what's happening within Africa in terms of its development?
First of all, Africa is waking up.
It's growing since the last seven, eight years, around five percent per year.
And that's, well, starting from zero, five percent is not a big change.
But, you know, somebody calls this African renaissance.
No, renaissance is too much.
But fermentation, yes, there is a new feeling, you know.
But this clearly has two main reasons.
First of all, the Chinese competition.
Second, the increase of raw materials in the first stage.
But what I found that European Union is the most generous donor to Africa.
Much more than anybody else.
But the European policy is completely divided from in the interest of the different countries, you know.
You have a fantastic French presence in the former French speaking countries.
British, Americans in West Africa or some French country.
China is in a bilateral way, but China now has a relation, active relation, with 50 on 54 African countries.
So you have the only case in which you have a continental policy.
When the African leaders go to Beijing for the bilateral meeting between Africa and China,
there are, you know, there is some sort of triumph, you know.
Everything, you know, fireworks, everything, you know.
And decision making policy very quick, of course, with also many negative aspects.
They don't care about human rights, about, you know, no Washington consensus, you know.
But the result is that you have more and more continental Chinese policy.
With another substantial difference, but there is nothing to do.
Looking at Africa, you have the only case in history in which there is a country exporting goods, capital, technology and people together.
Goods, capital, technology and people together.
And this will be, will go on for only 20 years and then the demography will temper down that, you know.
But other 20 years, you know.
Look, nobody knows because even that was not, no, people are not interested to that, you know.
When the Libyan war started, in four days they were transferred from Libya to China 38,800 workers.
38,800 in Libya.
When I, five years ago, I asked to put Africa, you know, the Algerian president, you know,
what about the Chinese? What about the Chinese?
He answered me, look, I, Algeria is a young people country, so I needed a very big, a very deep necessity to have a social housing program.
I made an auction, the price of Chinese was half of the Italians and of the French, so the Chinese got it.
The concept, 25,000 Chinese came to Algeria from the top architect to the last bricklayer.
They deliver the houses like a Swiss clock, he told me, you know.
And then each year 5,000 Chinese stop working but stay in Algeria.
They get married with Algerian girls and now, you know, they do some sort of small business group, you know, that I strongly need, you know.
Car repair shops, let's say, building small real estate and so on.
Then after five years, last June, when, before going to the hospital, you know, I met him again and asked, what about the Chinese?
And as I told you four years ago, now we have 25,000 Chinese with Algerian citizenship and for my economy is good, you know.
Of course this is not the same with black Africa because Chinese don't get married easily with black girls and so on.
But they are not only in Prato, they are everywhere in the world, you know.
And we are not elaborating a policy vis-à-vis this new type of challenge, you know.
That is different, that is different, you know.
President, I think we've been very disciplined.
We've been talking for 45 minutes and we haven't asked you about the economic crisis.
Austerity, growth, banking union, all these issues which are in some part at the center of the European debate.
So I know we could talk for another 45 minutes just about this but maybe you can give us some headlines of your thinking about how we manage the economic crisis
and your ideas and perspective for the future.
Well, it's easier for me how we didn't manage the economic crisis, you know.
But I start from something that seems to be normal, that only decisions about the economic crisis have been taken by a non-political body, the European Central Bank.
This is absolutely incredible, absolutely incredible, you know.
But all the other decisions taken by the Council are very peripheral.
No, but how to tackle the crisis was clearly a...
But even in this, why...
The crisis started from the United States.
This is a gift of our friends.
But immediately Obama injected in the economy 800 billion dollars, immediately.
They did everything different from the past, saving the motorcar industry and all the decisions that must be taken.
You know, a purely Keynesian decision.
Now nobody dares to pronounce the name of Keynes, you know.
But they did the Keynesian policy.
China did the same.
Five hundred eighty-five billion dollars.
Well, they say four trillion renbinbi.
I don't know, you know, the rate of it.
But they were four trillion renbinbi.
That is equivalent to five hundred.
So in terms of percentage more than the Americans did, you know, in terms of GDP.
And Europe, what has done Europe?
Nothing.
Well, because of that, the Greek crisis started.
No decision has been taken.
And the Greek problem was a very small problem.
Absolutely unimportant.
With 30 billion euros could be solved.
But there were elections in North Rhine, Westphalia.
And so the Germans didn't want to take any decision.
And when the decision was taken, don't forget the night after the election,
the 30 billion became 300 billion.
Because the speculation has done its normal job.
Speculate, you know.
We cannot blame speculation.
The job, Europe has done its job.
And so the reason why then the banks were suffering and so on
was the lack of a simple counter cyclical policy.
And now things went on in the same situation with a very peculiar German attitude,
you know, in which the business community was not against more solidarity.
But the political mood was that any exception to a severe policy,
any Keynesian policy was a gift to lazy people or to southern people, you know.
So we started to have this split.
And all the summits, they were spent in trying to have some sort of minor agreement
to avoid the clash between these two ideas, you know.
And now I speak as an Italian, you know, forgive me for a while,
but I have this vice to be Italian, you know.
And I don't, I never asked to German or to European leaders
to have an exception to the Maastricht rules.
We signed the obligation, we have to stick on that.
Even if I cannot forget when I was president of the European Commission,
in the first big meeting, the German in France under Italian presidency,
they decided that the 3% rule was not a rule, you know.
And they put the Commission completely in a corner, you know.
But anyway, this is the past.
But I never, I don't ask to make an exception to the rules,
but simply to make a policy that is consistent with the necessity of overcoming a crisis.
And I don't understand as an economist a country that did not grow,
is growing now a little more than 1%, I mean Germany.
But they have a surplus in the balance of trade that is three in terms of GDP,
almost three times bigger than the Chinese now.
China surplus was 10% of Chinese GDP, now is 2.6%.
German surplus is 7%.
Surplus, not substantial growth, no inflation, but danger of deflation.
I don't understand why you don't put fire in your engine.
Clearly they don't want to do, you know, and there is no common policy,
and so I cannot do anything.
But really, if you ask me as you ask why we didn't manage to get out of the crisis,
the reason is like that, you know.
And I don't understand that we have to make reforms, we have to do everything, you know,
but we could do reforms much better if the European economy grows 1.5 points more than now.
There could be, you know, and also we could avoid the danger of deflation,
because remember, Professor, that we are not far away from the Japanese syndrome
to have 20 years of stagnation, you know, because don't think that...
Inflation is far too low, which means the debt problem will actually not go away either.
Regardless of how much austerity, you won't end up with lower debt if you have low inflation and low growth.
You need one or other or both to solve a debt problem.
And also with unemployment, you may get higher growth, but jobless growth for a while in Europe.
So how does Europe put fire in the engine of growth?
Well, the simple way to do it is like the Americans or the Chinese did, not only print money,
but for example, you know, I am not a German minister, so I don't want to dictate anything,
but Germany has... Well, first of all, the first decision could be let us do a European plan
to link together all the pipelines with the Ukrainian case and all the electrical wires.
We have now a gasification station in Spain that have an enormous overcapacity
because there are no pipes linking to France.
You know, and also politically, when I was prime minister, I spent a weekend in Poland
talking with the two twins, the Kaczynski, when they were in power,
because they were furious for the pipeline coming directly from Russia to Germany, you know,
saying this is against Poland. My answer was very simple.
Let us put in front of the European Council a project to link all the European pipelines.
So there is no German link, no Polish link, no Italian link. There is a European link.
And think how we are stronger vis-à-vis the Russia, if you have a common policy.
Ah, but it was nothing to do. Now the first thing that we could do is a very simple project.
Second, enhance research. Third, Germany in terms of infrastructure, in my opinion,
is less endowed than France, so they have a lot of room to spend in infrastructure.
So they are, and I am not inventing very strange ideas, you know, very simple,
but discuss it together in order to have the common solidarity to do them, you know.
And we have not to invent the wheel, simply to have a common decision, you know.
And I really am very, and this is why I am not so theological position, you know.
Let's say you could easily make some movement without being accused to change your strategy.
This is why some correction, not so radical as I told before, could be done.
So Italy assumes the presidency of the Union in July.
If Mr. Renzi was to ask you what should be the Italian priorities for the Italian presidency,
what would be your number one, two and three that you would give him?
Oh, I have extensively written about that in terms of policy.
If we, as I told, if we put our fist on the table alone, we break our hand.
If we make an alternative policy with French, with Spanish, with Belgium,
with all the countries that need that, this is what we have to do, you know,
simply making a common project for a change of policy, not anti-German,
not because it would be stupid and without any common sense,
but simply in order to get out of the crisis together and avoiding it.
You know, I'm also worried about the social situation, you know.
I am surprised that with such a malaise nothing happens.
Imagine this situation 25 years ago, imagine.
But clearly now people are so accustomed to this new phase of our history
that we have not even any major tension, you know.
Luckily, you have not any major tension, but the malaise is so diffused.
So I have already written and told to anybody, you know,
that it is not easy because even the countries I listed, you know,
each of them thinks to be better than the others, you know.
For the French to make a common action with the Italians
is some sort of lowering the status, you know.
The Spanish are in a moment, I think, to be out of the crisis, you know.
The Italians refused the Troika help also, I think,
also because of initial pride, you know.
So it's not easy, but simply we have to change policy.
So if it's not changed because of a different political situation
after the election, this must be an alternative proposal.
But even this is not a debate.
The Italian president is very complicated, you know.
Very complicated because the elections are the 25th of May.
Then there will be 15 days for the European Court ratification and all that.
Then, let's say, half of June, the 20th of June,
the parliament has the first meeting.
Then they have to elect the members of the commission, you know.
And then the government must appoint the commissioners
and the president of the commission.
Then nobody reminds that the parliament must make an examination
of all the commissioners one by one.
And so 28 examinations.
And because the parliament must demonstrate to be a strong parliament,
few of them will be blocked.
And so there will be a second examination.
And we are going far beyond summer, you know.
So it's, well, maybe also with this empty space you can work better, you know.
But I simply, I'm telling you that will be a different semester, you know.
And nobody talks about that, whether it's better or worse for a presidency.
But it's a completely different landscape, you know.
You will not have...
So maybe your last word should be your kind of vision for the Europe that we should have.
Well, my vision is very simple.
I am an ugly federalist, you know.
But my answer is what will be the most viable strategy
and most, let's say, to approach this.
So probably we shall have a multiple speed Europe.
As we have now, let's say, with the euro and non euro,
but even deeper than that, waiting for the British decision.
Clearly, I have not in my mind that the UK gets out of Europe.
Maybe they will be inside Europe with the existing agreement
and nothing more than that, you know.
Or if the referendum decides to get out.
So the euro countries, let us call them euro countries,
but anyway, let's say some core Europe,
will go on in the direction I described before.
And others will remain in the wider, mainly free trade with something more Europe, you know.
This is the more probable outcome that we shall have in the future.
My desire is a 28 or 29 with Serbia and others, you know.
Let's say 30 countries, you're getting together going on, you know.
But Europe is based on democracy and so British people will decide
and others will decide whether to be part of it.
But certainly we cannot stop waiting for Godot, you know,
because it will be a disaster for everybody
and there will be a point in which Europe will go in disarray.
And how long can be this interim phase?
Maybe also long, but I do think that in some moment
there will be a stronger leadership in Ghana.
You know, in my experience it was easier to get results,
even if it was so difficult to run the European Commission at the moment of change,
because for different reasons, but both, and in different context,
but both Kohl and the French leaders, you know, Chirac,
they were strongly pro-European, you know.
The option was pro-Europe, you know.
When I remember when I was telling to Kohl,
look, we cannot have the euro without strengthening
the pillars in defense of the euro, you know.
If some crisis or some unexpected events come, we have no instruments.
His answer was not we have done enough.
But I remember, you shall never forget,
he told me, I wanted the euro and I want the euro
because my brother died in the war.
And I wanted the thing that will never happen, you know.
And on your economic issues, you are Italian,
and remember that Rome was not done in one day.
And so in the next year, step by step,
we shall do what needs to be done.
Now the effort to impose the euro to the German has been already too much,
and we cannot do more than that.
But step by step everything will be done.
And it was so credible, you know, in this moment, so normal,
because it was the moment of enlargement,
it was the moment of, let's say, there is no other option.
And it was, for me, it was really convincing, you know.
But then the leaders changed it.
The leaders changed it and, you know, we need 30 summits
to have a very, let's say, weak decision on Europe, you know.
And then we have also had the political change, you know,
because in my time there was an engine with two pistons,
you know, France and Germany.
Now we have one leader, you know,
and so a strong, very strong country.
And so the temptation of a leading country
is always stronger than the temptation of a country
that has to share power, you know.
So this is why it's so complicated now, you know.
And, of course, I am convinced that in the globalization
there is no country able to, not even Germany,
to challenge the globalization, you know.
I always compare the European situation
with what was happening in the Renaissance, you know.
The Italian states, they were leading, you know.
It's not a rhetoric view.
Florence, Milan, Genoa, they were leading in finance,
in the military field, in all technology, the optical, you know.
And the first globalization came
because the discovery of America was globalization.
And we didn't unite,
and we didn't have the economic of scale
that England, France and Spain had,
and we disappeared from the world map for four sectors.
Europe is in the same situation.
But I think that wisdom will prepare.
But if we don't stick together, we disappear from the world map.