è fondata. E quindi, per essere in grado di svegliare e mobilizzare di nuovo le risorse simboliche
di significazione, è venuta per noi, più e più, uno dei modi per raggiungere gli obiettivi
e le idee dei fondatori. Grazie molto, e grazie a Presidente Prodi, di nuovo, per essere qui.
Ok, buongiorno a tutti. È davvero un onore per me essere qui, in questo templo di scienze,
e per inaugurare questo maestro di degree in internazionale di sicurezza, che è una cosa
nuova in Italia, molto selezionale, e penso che sarà molto utile creare l'elite necessaria
Non è la prima volta che parlo in fronte di un pubblico che sa molto di più di ciò che faccio,
perché ogni politico fa ciò. Ma comunque, in questo caso è particolarmente, diciamo,
molto imbarazzante, ma io solo giustifico me, dicendo che la mia ignoranza è enciclopedica,
quindi posso bilanciarmi. Guardate, abbiamo 40 minuti per parlare di l'evoluzione della politica mondiale
e del ruolo d'Europa. Prima di tutto, sono così, diciamo, sorpreso, ma anche,
you know, find it normal that almost everybody in the political science elite has some nostalgia
about the Cold War. The nostalgia for the Cold War is coming back as a mantra, you know,
and if you think that during the Cold War, of course the young student, they don't remember it,
but we were living frightened by the idea of a nuclear explosion, a big clash, a nuclear war and so on and so on and so on.
And so this nostalgia means that something wrong went in history after the end of the Cold War.
And the reasons of nostalgia is that after that we passed from the Cold War to the Monopolar War,
you know, Monopolar War that, say, United States were the only power able to run the war and could alone do it.
This was the common opinion. And to the, you know, to the scholars, they can remind two publications,
one the end of history and the other one the American Century. The meaning was the same.
We entering in a period of end of history because there will be at least an American Century.
American Century meaning that one country could have dominated the world alone.
And history went in a different way, you know.
Well, let's just go back a bit. And this opinion was shared not only by some intellectual,
but was shared by political leadership, you know, and I do think I am convinced that the Iraqi War,
it was simply the concrete manifestation of monopolarity.
The idea that you could put the seal of the American domination in a war easy to win,
that was supposed to endure a few weeks, and that was the seal of the American power.
And things went different since that moment. Then we can quote the Afghanistan War,
but any case of bringing a war outside the country, you know, in a foreign place,
it demonstrated that the challenge of a country to dominate the world
was much more difficult than any political scientist could imagine, you know.
And since the moment there was the starting of dangerous local, non-local conflicts,
local in the sense that they were not world war, but non-local,
because all these conflicts from Iraq to Afghanistan, they completely moved the structure
of the political structure of the states that were around the place in which the war started.
And this conflict, they eroded a lot of the American strength.
Look, I have to be clear, U.S. Army and U.S. strength, U.S. leadership is strong even now.
The United States is the strongest country in the world, by far.
The military expenditure of the United States, depending upon strategy,
is from 43 to 50 percent of all the world military budget.
The technology is by far the more advanced.
But the society changed.
Well, second, United States is the only country that has, let's say,
avant-posts and troops everywhere in the world.
I don't know whether there are 600 or 800 American, let's say, barracks
expanded in the world, but there is no other case.
But in spite of that, U.S. is unable to exercise, in practical terms,
this power for a simple reason.
Because of this negative event of the Bush and post-Bush wars,
the American society is absolutely against any idea of having back dead bodies
from abroad, Republican, Democratic.
I think even Trump cannot tell to the electorate,
we shall have again young Americans died coming back from the various world countries.
And this is a change, a total change in the world strategy.
Now you have United States that are very active with the drones,
with the planes, with bombing, but not with the boots.
And you cannot take the power of the world without boots,
without direct influence.
And this is the major change,
but clearly does not mean that the American is becoming isolationist.
Maybe with Trump could be more isolationist,
but I think that even Trump cannot go too far in this direction
because the military and even more economic links
with the United States, with the rest of the world,
Europe, China and everywhere is too deep now
and any really isolationist policy
could devastate really the American economy.
So don't trust literally what Trump is expressing in the campaign
because he cannot put to the end of the meaning.
And certainly the foreign American policy
has been from some, even under Obama
has been from many point of view disappointing.
He started with a great scenario, great engagement
if you think only to the Cairo speech about Africa.
He has given really hope, a great hope to all the African countries
and nothing happened, almost nothing happened.
Clearly Obama has been engaged more to try to
let's say slim down the Bush heritage
than to do something new.
And this work was going too long.
Probably it was too slow only in the last year.
He's taken some initiative with Iran, nuclear base,
but look in the end of the mandate
in which the power of the president is not so important.
But in spite of the internal fairly successful policy
not only even if with big dangers for the budget for the future
he has given new health system to
dozens of millions of people
and lucky for him
but a new energy policy made United States stronger than before
and in the end United States
overcame the crisis much better than any other big power in the world.
Don't forget that the crisis started
and was originated by United States
but United States went out quickly, very quickly
because let's say different from the American tradition of Reagan
they put $800 billion on the table immediately
to react to the crisis.
Obama overcame the crisis
with some sort that we could call Keynesian policy
not policy like the predecessor and the new energy policy.
Of course the shale gas and shale oil
have been a blessing for the American economy
but in spite of that
I repeat, no possibility of being dominating on the policy
and last observation
the moving of the core attention
in theory from the Atlantic to the Pacific
the obsession with China
they moved and all the problems came from here
and not from there
it was a strange situation
China is an obsession
but the problem they come from Middle East and Europe
from the Mediterranean and from the Middle East
so with this lot of proxy wars
in which Americans are not engaged mainly
and they try to engage less and less
but they are still engaged
the last example of that
I insist on that because it is a great change of the world
if you take the Iraqi war
the United States spent 90% of the cost of the world
could be 85, could be 95
if you take the Libya one
the cost was 15% France, 15% UK
15% United States, 10% Italy
and then Gulf and so on
so you have this engagement
and Obama also repented
he blamed himself for having accepted
to enter into this war
he tried to disengage from this foreign policy
but it is some sort of heritage of the past
from which they could disengage
but in the meanwhile
when these things went on
the world has changed
first of all China
China is really the new fact
the new event of the world
growth, not only growth
but also technological change
the scientific role of China will become dominant
even that in the future
but a country who arrived to the world
with a completely different strategy
arrived, I am inexact
came back again
because even in the Renaissance or the 16th century
China was dominating the world economy
isolated but dominating
if you read the historians
they say that in the 16th century
the wealthiest place in the world
were China and Tuscany
so I was not alive in that time
but anyway I do trust
I do trust historians
but in this case the new China is different
because the first time in history
that a country has a new strategy
operates in the world economy with goods
selling goods that we buy every day
exporting people
emigrates everywhere
in Africa, in Italy and so on
but technology and capital together
if you analyze the world history
it never happened that a country could
put together
and it is incredible
incredible because they did
in the world scale
6 years ago I was in Algeria
asking Bouteflika
what about Chinese?
I went out of Chinese
and I told look professor
we had the problem of social housing
we needed to build social housing
and the price of Chinese
was half of the Italians and the French
and so they came here 25,000 Chinese
they delivered the houses
as regular as a Swiss clock
and you know
and then what he had
every year 5000 Chinese
stop working and other come
and get married here in Algeria
and so we have a small entrepreneurship
that I need so much
2 years ago I asked how is going
and he told me look
as I told you 5 years ago
but now we have already
25,000 Chinese
with Algerian citizenship
you know this is
when they are quicker to give
Algerian citizenship
than in Italy to give Italian citizenship
certainly but the type of
strategy is quite interesting
and for the future
it will change the world
and clearly China
has a lot of problems
I have too short time
to analyze them deeply
but I only list them
banks
from the economic point of view
banks and the overproduction
of many traditional sectors
from the political point of view
is a strong
political power struggle
there is a real power struggle
but
and corruption
and also a deep demographic problem
because the one child policy
was started in 1978
and so generation with low people
so you have a strange world
now China is 1.1 billion
and 380 million people
will be
the middle of the center will be
142, 43 billion
India now is 11 million people
will be 1.7 billion
and almost 800,000 million
in the middle of the century
it's incredible this change of the world
but
and this is the point
in order to
let's say go on with the development
power in China has been
concentrated
we have a more central power now
that anytime
after Mao Zedong
Xi has together the army
the party and the government
and the anti-corruption
fight that is incredible
if you analyze the Chinese
analysts today
consider that it would be between
150,000 to 400,000 people
under accusation
incredible
but
is also an instrument
to concentrate power
and so now you have
since few months also a more
assertive foreign policy
if you analyze from inside
the infrastructure investment bank
and the proposal of the Silk Road
these are very intelligent
because China was put always out
of any power in the World Bank
they created the World Bank
and because of the new Chinese power
even United Kingdom decided
to enter into this bank
against United States
and it was in my knowledge the first time
in many decades that United Kingdom
made a policy different from United States
because the interest
to have the RMB
let's say traded in the London Stock Exchange
instead of worst trade
it was much more important than
the political interest of the United States
and the Silk Road in theory
is the old historical link
between Europe and China
but the real immediate consequence
are new ports
an increasing influence of China
around China
Kazakhstan, Uzbekistan
till Iran and Pakistan
and Bangladesh where new ports
are built it's clearly a new
assertive China
both politically and economically
and you know
and this is done
as I hinted before
through a totally different
strategy of the American
or European that is
concentrating power
I sum up
this phase of Chinese policy
telling that is totally different from
the Leopard, the Catopard
in Palermo everything needed to change
in order that nothing could change
in Beijing, in Pechino
nothing must change in order that the society
could change
and this is the real assertive
Chinese policy and is really efficient
in many discussions I had
with Chinese officials
they were simply telling me
how can you run your countries
not meaning Italy, meaning Europe and United States
with elections every day
and you don't think to the future
you think only to the short term
and the problems are more and more long term
problems research, education, health and so on
defense and so on
and this is
will be in the future the great problem
of the power in mankind
and clearly in this
and from the
merely from the pure
military point of view clearly as I hinted before
they are much inferior in navy
they are much inferior in aviation
they are much inferior to United States
in land troops but
they are doing an incredible
effort in the new
evolution of the world that is cyber war
Chinese obsessed
by cyber war
they are making incredible progress
the only mistake the Chinese are doing
they are buying football teams
when you buy football teams you may have all the worst
consequences in the world
follow this chapter because it will be the end of China
no but
and I insist on that
because in the evolution
of mankind of the strength in mankind
the real economic
and then political
center are the new networks
I always tell to the students that they are
like the caravans after the
discovery of America and the new networks
Google, Alibaba
Apple
Ebay
are all American and Chinese
and we are out of that
and these are the new power of the world
when you think you know of course
the Italian media sometimes
which are a little not too
dedicated to the analysis but
when you find that Apple was fine
well not fine it was obliged
to pay 13
billion tax
to Ireland
that's 13 billion
taxes a lot
but then I was given a glance
to the Apple
let's say
notes you know
and they have 260
billion cash
260 billion cash
so it's a look at
this is the new power in the world
I don't I am not talking only about
the cultural power you know that is
even stronger and more important you know but please
we are going in the hands
of them
and when I am furious
with people who don't understand Europe
I say look but how can we have a world
in the future being out of that
and no one in Europe
is now able to enter
in this vital field of the new
world
oh well I have the tintea
I don't know
this is a bad thinking you know
a bad thought but sometimes I wonder
if Germany does not think to be
strong enough to do it alone you know
because otherwise it's difficult
for me to understand the policy which
the interest should be to
let's say to share
the leadership
with others in order to be strong
and enough to
let's say
accept this challenge
but you know so is life
oh well I am too
I have to be
a little more in a hurry in my explanation
in the meanwhile we have
the evolution of China
another very interesting and complete
evolution is
Russia
Russia after the disruption of
Soviet Union was in such
an incredible weak and bad
situation that nobody could ever think
could resurrect
and after the clearly
the healthy humiliation
you know it was
Putin
was able to
reorganize Russia you know
so I do remember that
when
Putin was
rising but just in the beginning you know
Gorbachev came to visit me telling
look I have a message very important message
there is a man a new man in Russia
he has a curriculum a CV
that is the worst they could imagine
but he's the only one who can save
Russia and
be and keep Russia linked
to Europe
then they went you know they went
disruption you know but in the beginning
this was like Erdogan you know
when Erdogan started
Erdogan was our hope
our hope you know because he was
he was open to the
as mayor of Istanbul he was open to the
western world and it was
less inclined to have
a pyramidal society
with an army that was dominating
everything you know it's
but then the evolution is
evolution your power is changing a lot of
people you know
so this was
and then you know
now the situation is
I don't tell you
anecdotes of how Yeltsin
was really endangering
the image of Russia you know so when
Putin came he started
to put Russia as a
regional power and then world power
in spite of the enormous
weakness of Russia
because Russia is really weak you know from
economic point of view you know it's a demographic
demography is a disaster
is a disaster you know now Russia is
145 million people
will be 100 and
half of the center will be 110
and in Siberia
the biggest
of the world now we have
east of Ural we have 45 million and
we'll be 25 million you know and
you have a small river and then you have 1.3
billion Chinese you know so it's
and you know
but he
sorry
he
he started to reorganize
you know the spirit and the
let's say the identity more the
identity of Russia than anything
else and make a very
let's say very policy
in the Middle East free from any constraints
you know so
in Syria when you have
Putin that
he fights against ISIS like us
but with the only army
existing Assad
that was the enemy of Western
world you have clearly a strategic
advantage and he exploited a lot of this
local situation you know
of course
exploiting the fact that he has no constraints
in the decision making
decision making
policy you know and
clearly
friend of Europe is not friend of
Europe in this moment but why
why because
Putin is obsessed by NATO
the only problem Putin is NATO
not European Union he was very
you know very let's say open
to cooperation with European Union
but and in the moment
of history we understood that you know the last
decision I have taken in my last government
in 2008 it was
clearly to be
clear it was the day after the
confidence vote I was already almost out
of politics you know it was the NATO
the NATO
the NATO Council
was in Bucharest
and France Italy and Germany
they voted against the mission
of NATO in Ukraine
and Georgia for simple reason
that we needed to have
sort of and
you know it was the moment in which
we had the illusion to have a united
Europe from
new and old countries and make a common policy
but it was clear
that the Baltic countries
Poland
they had
let's say such a tension
with Russia that this was the first
the most impossible
the most important
priority for
for that country
so now in Europe
clearly the
the Ukrainian case is poisoning
all the nations
making Ukraine that is making
difficult even the Syrian agreement
because it's clear that this is my point
you cannot have any peace in this
historical moment without an agreement between
United States and Russia is absolutely
clear
you see how
they try and they go back
so till the moment in which we have
not disagreement we cannot have
some sort of settlement
in this
really
and last reflection
is
the role of Europe in this
three great power movement is
absolutely marginal you know for a simple
reason that we are divided
in theory I repeat we are number one in
industrial production number one in the world
number one in export
we have scientific
reservoir that is fantastic
but being divided we cannot be part
of this new
world policy you know
and there is no point in
European foreign policy which no one
important issue in which Europe
agreed you know Iraqi war we are
divided Afghanistan you know Libya
we are divided and clearly
it's a situation in which
going on in this direction we cannot have a role
in the world you know
the last effort for European army
is absolutely
a good effort in the right direction but
with slim hope to be
an entity you know because
army is the real core of any
sovereignty and this moment is
in my opinion so difficult
to put together
and the other
the other consequence
is that being divided
even in economy our performance
is much slower than the American one
we since the beginning of the crisis
we grow half of United States
in the last term United States
were a little going down but all the forecasts
are that we shall go on
growing half of United States
you know and so in the longer
in the longer run
the difference will be
enormous
also after Brexit because
Britain is not certainly
an economic power
British industry is less
than the Italian one much less
but from the financial point of view
and from the military point of view
it was a strong
very strong country the British army
is by far the strongest
in Europe you know
but even more
what why the
role is so change that from
Canada to United States to Australia
New Zealand
many African counties
India
Europe was analyzed
only through the British classes
and you know
for India
Europe without Britain
is nothing
we have all these consequences
but I think that we
could organize ourselves
also in the new more restricted area
but we have to decide what to do with Brexit
and we don't
have a policy with Brexit
and my scenario will be that
the British will go all
and on and on and on and on
negotiation will go on and on and on and on
and the meanwhile they can take
decision for taxation for ta ta ta ta ta ta ta ta
and we shall find ourselves even in this
almost internal
negotiation absolutely weaker
than UK
you know simply because we are
divided you know and
well this is the
scenario you know I
omitted
two appendix that should be put aside
but I am to the end of my
of the time that has been given that is
migration and the role of United Nations
for migration
I consider that the
fear that migration have brought
the terror of migration is a consequence
of the war migration in quantity
was similar than now
but because it was controlled
and now uncontrolled the consequences
on people you know I always bring the example
how many times Gaddafi was
calling me and telling me I send you
votes of people he never did because
there was a state you know there was
some sort of negotiation always you know
and now impossible
but we have to tackle the problem in terms
of development because
I tell only one figures you know
median life
not average median life in Italy is
between 46 and 47 years
median life in sub-Saharan
area Mali Burkina
Chad is
between 17 and 18
you know when you have these figures it's
you understand everything there is nothing else
to add you know so this flow
and clearly in this framework
I should end telling look
let us
ask action from United Nations
and so on and in my experience
United Nations are very important
they have been very positive and active
but in small conflicts
only
important because they can have small conflict
millions of people dying and so on and so on but
where we move from a conflict
that is under
attention of some of the five veto
powers then
UN action stops you know
so we open another chapters how
to avoid that you know but
not easy in this moment
so this is the scenario
of the change in front
who we are now
this is the evolution
of the world I have been
con qualche merito culturale
da non dimenticare grazie
chi vuole parlare?
tre domande allora perché se non so rispondere
con tre me la cavo uno per volta
è diventato un problema capisci?
chi ha il microfono chi vuole parlare?
serena giusti
italiana italiana italiana
grazie per la presentazione io torno un attimo
sull'Unione Europea lei è stato uno dei promotori
della politica europea di vicinato
considerando adesso il vicinato
vediamo che ci sono molte falle di conflitto
molte aree di crisi ha citato
l'Ucraina ma insomma conosciamo il caso
della giorgia della trasmistria
di tutto il mediterraneo
vedendo questa politica al ritroso
secondo lei la commissione l'Unione Europea
ha fatto qualche errore di valutazione
soprattutto nel a mio avviso
non considerare un attore importante
come la Russia che poi abbiamo visto
ha reagito in maniera molto assertiva
un'altra veloce demanda su Brexit
secondo lei il Regno Unito potrà giocare
in futuro un ruolo da potenza autonoma
oppure rafforzerà
la partnership con gli Stati Uniti
considerando il punto interrogativo
che avvolge l'esito delle presidenziali
grazie
ne fate due le facciamo un'altra
possibilmente da parte degli studenti
del MIS
ormai è possibile anche degli allievi della scuola
non vorrei rubare il microfono
dopo solo studenti
qui facciamo un primo round
io partirei dall'ultima frase
siamo vicini al punto
di non ritorno dell'Unione Europea
penso che per forza di cose
chiedere a lei che ha avuto questa esperienza importante
è da dove si parte perché dal punto di vista
di essere a un punto di non ritorno della crisi
economica siamo ancora lì sulla crisi migratoria
siamo lì sulla rilevante
della politica estera siamo lì
credo che questo sia evidente a tutti gli attori
quelli nazionali, alla classe intellettuale
anche alla gente comune
da dove si può pensare di partire per evitare di arrivare nel barato
tre domande
politica europea di vicinato
è una delle cose
che la Presidente della Commissione Europea
non sono mai riuscito a fare
è avere un dibattito parlamentare
su quali sono i confini dell'Europa
tre volte si sono sempre tirati indietro
proprio perché c'erano tutti i diversi pareri
c'erano tutte le idee
io avevo inventato allora una politica
che secondo me adesso andrebbe molto bene
i confini muoviamoli eccetera eccetera
ma intanto facciamo per tutti i paesi
che stanno attorno all'Europa
dalla Bielorussia fino al Marocco
passando per Israele, la Siria eccetera
una proposta che si chiama
Ring of friends
si chiamava l'anello degli amici
o neighbor policy, la politica di vicinato
cioè che tutti questi paesi possano
potessero senza essere membri dell'Unione Europea
infatti un terzo nome era
everything but institutions
avere, aprire su tutti i capitoli negoziati
dei rapporti con l'Unione Europea
in modo di avere questa
purtroppo non si è riusciti ad andare avanti
perché è cominciato il cammino all'indietro
e quindi il primo errore è stato quello
di non avere una politica generale per il vicinato
alcuni altri, sempre su questo capitolo
dicono ma si è aperto troppo in fretta i paesi dell'est
io ritengo ancora
che quello che abbiamo fatto
sia stata la cosa più bella per la pace del mondo
e per l'esportazione della democrazia
l'unico caso al mondo di vera esportazione della democrazia
perché negoziazioni
loro votavano eccetera
e poi mi chiedo anche che cosa sarebbe oggi
se la Polonia fosse come l'Ucraina
problemi ne abbiamo
ma ne abbiamo più nei paesi che sono fuori
che non nei paesi che sono dentro
questo è il discorso che mi impongo
sull'errore di valutazione
si ne sono stati fatti molti perché
l'Ucraina, soprattutto ma in tutta la zona
di confini con la Russia
è stata politicamente organizzata come un problema di politica interna
e non come un problema di politica interna
c'è un problema di politica interna americana
cioè il voto polacco
il voto baltico
che ha un sentimento antirusso
che arriva dalla storia
ma che arriva... io ho avuto la riunione
con i fratelli Kaczynski, coi due gemelli
prima che uno morisse
perché la signora Merkel aveva detto
visto che ha i buoni rapporti con la Polonia
litigavano per il gasdotto che doveva andare sotto il mare
se poi... è passato un weekend a Marsavia
e sentire un tale odio
contro i russi e contro i tedeschi
la storia
scusate, la storia
ha dei pesi enormi
quando Schirach, in modo del tutto inaspettato
ah beh, sto parlando dell'italiano, scusate
propose allargamento
propose di iniziare i negoziati con la Turchia
vabbè, nessuno lo s'aspettava
fummo un po' disorientati, eravamo a Maersk
però alla fine, abbiamo detto, ma sì
eccetto il cancelliero austriaco
ricordate l'assedio di Vienna
la storia è la storia
errori di valutazione ci sono stati
certamente
errori
su una minore durezza russa e su una maggiore
saggezza nostra, cioè sono stati errori
simmetrici, noi abbiamo preso l'Ucraina
invece come un ponte, come un capo di battaglia
e non si risolverà mai
il problema ucraino se noi
non riprendiamo a prendere l'Ucraina come un ponte
noi a dare la garanzia assoluta che non entrerà
e i russi danno la garanzia
nelle zone russi, una autonomia
ma poi
li poi ci sono stati altri errori perché
la gara nell'essere dei ladroni
fra i filo russi e i filo occidentali
è stata una gara altro che olimpiadi
ho compreso le signore
con i capelli biondi
voglio dire che mi sono trovato
due volte al Presidente della Commissione Europea
andare a Kiev a mediare perché rubavano
il gas dai gasdotti con i tubi grandi così
allora voglio dire, quelle robe le fa solo il governo
non è che un privato cittadino può rubare da un gasdotto
in quel modo lì e il Paese è andato avanti
governato in questo modo insomma
queste sono le crude verità
Brexit, autonomia dagli USA o no
no, dovranno
difficile per un Paese con la Gran Bretagna
che ha tutta una serie di
rapporti economici, politici commerciali
che possa fare una politica dell'indipendente
il Brexit
si avverrà perché non ci si capisce più niente
avverrà ecco
comunque insomma
portano alla Gran Bretagna
verso gli USA perché poi è sempre stato
il problema britannico
voglio dire, io ho stato Presidente della Commissione a 15 e a 25 Paesi
ma era uguale
il problema era sempre la Gran Bretagna
perché con l'intelligenza
diplomatica
ho vedato che erano di gran lunga
dominanti dal punto di vista intellettuale
io andai Presidente della Commissione
pensando di essere sotto la burocrazia franco-tedesca
dominavano gli inglesi
prima perché erano bravissimi, secondo luogo perché
mentre coi tedeschi, coi francesi, coi italiani il giorno dopo
imparavano se non una socialista democristiana eccetera
bello e tuttora, io non so assolutamente
i miei collaboratori a che partita
appartenessero, erano figli di sua ma è stata la regina
e basta, guardate che questo dà una forza
straordinaria a un Paese, straordinaria
proprio
però se il Brexit avviene eccetera
è difficilissimo che non si
rafforzi il legame con gli Stati Uniti
proprio perché erano sempre
la vera
la Gran Bretagna è uscita da Europa perché
nel cuore anche se non nel dibattito
c'è sempre l'alternativa americana
e questo è quello che io penso
punto di un ritorno è da dove partire
ma siamo realistici per l'Europa
cosa volete, l'Europa è cambiata 10, 12 anni fa
la definizione di Europa quando ero Presidente
la più bella definizione era
Europe is a union of minorities
è un'unione europea, è un'unione di minoranze
e oggi non lo potete capire
oggi c'è un Paese leader
soprattutto dopo l'uscita della Gran Bretagna
è l'indebolimento della Francia
perché un altro capitolo europeo
noi stiamo a guardare l'Italia eccetera
è impressionante
in termini di perdita
di parità di dialogo
oggi c'è un Paese leader unico
che si chiama Germania
e quindi da chi partire
se non c'è la comprensione
dell'interesse generale
da parte della Germania è difficile
io porto sempre l'esempio
finita la guerra gli Stati Uniti dominavano in tutto
e hanno fatto il piano Marshall
ma non perché si iscrivessero al San Vincenzo de Paoli
semplicemente perché hanno il loro interesse
io pensavo e penso tutt'ora
che si interesse il tedesco
a mettersi nell'indessante un'Europa forte
il caso greco erano 30 miliardi di euro
era una sciocchezza
a forza di rinviare per le elezioni eccetera
sono diventati 300 miliardi in pochi mesi
in tre mesi
allora voglio dire
se non si risolve
facevi conti che la Grecia esporta
come la provincia in cui sono nato
come la provincia di Reggio Emilia
insomma non si riesce a risolvere un problema del genere
2% è prodotto l'ordo europeo
e ciò
vuol dire proprio che c'è
che la politica interna
ha preso talmente il dominio
che non si guarda null'altro
quindi o c'è un cambiamento di questo tipo
oppure io non credo che ci sia il colasso
perché è uno svantaggio per tutti
ma vivacchiremo
ecco una parola che non sapevo dire in inglese
vivacchiremo
quindi è un vantaggio parlare l'italiano
una visione sul mondo, come diceva Goethe
quindi anche l'italiano col vivacchiremo ci dà un quadro
che l'inglese non ci avrebbe dato
tre studenti
prima gli studenti scusi
almeno che non si definisca come studenti alziano
vorrei sapere, dove va questo eroma?
l'euro che ne ha prodotto
si ha rovinato
la potenzia che è stata sconfitta
cosa mi risponde?
è una domanda che va fatta
l'euro non ci ha rovinato
ci ha rovinato la politica che è stata fatta
vede
l'euro
era il grande strumento
per un'Europa Unita
l'euro quando venne
fu salutato da tutti come
un fatto nuovo
e sapevamo benissimo
che l'euro doveva essere accompagnato
dagli strumenti di politica economica
che dovevano sorreggerlo
cioè armonizzazione fiscale
armonizzazione delle politiche
e quando io facevo presente a Col
queste cose
lui mi dava
una
risposta straordinaria
due risposte straordinarie
la prima dice che i tedeschi
non vogliono l'euro
ma io voglio l'euro
perché mio fratello è morto in guerra
non mi diceva perché la banca
cioè l'euro era il grande strumento
della coesione
che avrebbe fatto la nuova Europa
di cui abbiamo parlato fino ad adesso
quella che potrebbe reggere agli Stati Uniti
e alla Cina
e poi mi diceva un'altra cosa quando gli obiettavo
ma ci vogliono gli strumenti finanziari
mi diceva ma tu sei un italiano
e sai che Roma non è stata fatta in un giorno
a questo seguiranno quello che tu dici
e poi è cambiato il mondo
è cambiato l'euro, è cambiato il mondo
le miglazioni, la paura, le guerre
la politica americana, la politica russa
hanno sempre più diviso
ma il disegno dell'euro
era un disegno di unione progressiva
questo era il segno dell'euro
lei ha ragione se mi dice che poi non c'è stata
ma infatti
per sette anni andò benissimo
se per sette anni andò benissimo
non è stato l'euro la causa
ma è stato come
è stato applicato soprattutto dopo la crisi economica
Salve, buongiorno, grazie mille per la presentazione
lei ha parlato dell'evoluzione
Salve, sono Davide Orcitto
e sono una nuova matricola qui al Miss
sono molto contento di essere qui
e avevo una domanda un po' più specifica
sullo stesso topic di cui lei ha parlato
lei ha parlato dell'evoluzione delle politiche mondiali
e il ruolo dell'Europa
io vorrei spostare questa domanda al ruolo italiano in Europa
e più specificatamente vorrei sapere
come si raffigura lei
il ruolo italiano soprattutto come mediatore tra Europa e Stati Uniti
in uno scenario post Brexit
ringrazio
seconda
buongiorno, io anche sono una studentessa del Miss
si chiama
voce Francesca, volevo ringraziarla per il suo intervento
che ha toccato temi che riguarda il nostro corso di laurea
ma che sono di interesse generale
la mia domanda era un suo personale parere
sull'attuale congelamento del TTP
e invece l'avanzamento con gli accordi con il Canada
da parte dell'Unione Europea
buongiorno, Paolo Recaldini
sono collega dei miei colleghi
del suo intervento
ho scudato meglio la parte sulla Cina
perché ho studiato cinese
e sono stato con una borsa di studio
e volevo chiederle, perché io ho vissuto la situazione
da non cittadino però da persona normale
che stava a vivere
informata sui fatti
si prova a informarsi perché sa che non dicono tutto quello che si può sapere
volevo chiederle
sul ruolo della Cina in Africa, sappiamo che la Cina sta investendo un sacco
noi non sappiamo se c'è un piano perché giustamente non si può sapere
ma probabilmente c'è qualcosa di ben organizzato
volevo chiederle, dato che comunque l'Africa
non è molto lontana da noi
che ruolo potrebbe avere poi l'Europa
sia nel breve periodo che nel lungo periodo
proprio in rapporto alla potenza cinese
Dario, il ruolo italiano in Europa
è un ruolo
secondo me importante
anzi importantissimo
anche se non bisogna
pensare di esserci soli
quando pensiamo alla politica dobbiamo sempre
pensare al saggio
proverbio napoletano
che dice che non si può fare danza classica
se si ha il sedere basso
e allora
la politica
italiana in Europa
è importante perché siamo
non solo perché siamo fra i paesi fondatori
ma perché abbiamo 60 milioni di abitanti
siamo la seconda potenza industriale europea
ma quello che è importante
è che non possiamo mai
esercitare un potere in Europa
da soli
cioè il potere italiano che è forte
può essere concretizzato soltanto
con un rapporto fra i paesi
con altri paesi che ci diano
la forza di fare una politica
nel nostro legittimo interesse
e questo è un problema
serio
perché
chiaro che negli ultimi anni
noi avevamo tutto l'interesse
in una politica economica diversa
che però esigeva un rapporto con chi aveva gli stessi interessi
cioè la Spagna e la Francia
ma non c'è stato verso devo dire
la Francia come si è dimostrato
e è interessante
per il punto dei collochi con esperti parlamentari francesi
mai si distaccheranno
dall'asse con la Germania
questa è la risposta che a tu per tutti danno tutti
nel senso che preferiscono essere
i secondi serie A che i primi serie B
ecco
questo discorso che in fondo
il motore franco tedesco
e anche il centro d'Europa
pur essendo chiaramente
nelle cose che c'è
un motore sarà ancora due pistoli ma un pistone grande così
e l'altro grande così
ripeto
quindi
primo luogo
generale secondo
abbiamo una vocazione specifica
che è quella mediterranea
noi avevamo veri
carte in mano
uso l'imperfetto perché adesso sono meno
ma vere carte in mano per la politica mediterranea
la politica mediterranea forte
e devo dire che qui l'Unione Europea
non ne ho mai voluto sapere
quando io giravo
per il paese mediterraneo e durante la commissione europea
tutti mi dicevano ma voi guardate solo
a nord e a est
e io rispondevo ragionevolmente successo un fatto
politico disruptive
cioè del tutto luogo
che è la fine della Unione Sovietica
ma poi certamente ci sarà politica mediterranea
e invece questa non c'è stata
ma a fine delle cose più
scusatemi
a fine delle cose più elementarie mi ricordo la proposta
di fare l'università
dell'Ustamiste
io ero sedia a Catania, a Tunisia, a Barcellona
a Tripoli
due anni a nord, due anni a sud
metà professore del nord, metà professore del sud
metà di sud costava due soldi
io abbia Svezia, Gran Bretagna
che con l'idea
dei meridionali sciupuni
non ne volevano sapere
la banca del mediterraneo
no, è la BEI che abbastanza
infatti la BEI fa bene il mediterraneo
ma è diversa una banca europea
che opera nel mediterraneo da una banca con uguali
consigliere di amministrazione, uguali capitali
del nord e del sud
devo dire che c'è
stata una cescità
prolungata
probabilmente
è tutto il discorso che da dieci anni in qua
va, restringiamo il bilancio europeo
solo tutti i soldi buttati via
si è dato un'immagine
e lì la stampa Anglo-Sasson è stata impressionante
per me quest'anno vedere i Financial Times
che era contro la Brexit mi veniva da ridere
perché quello che non hanno detto
contro l'Europa, lo scioppio
il bilancio europeo
guardate che il bilancio dell'Unione Europea
è meno dell'un per cento
del prodotto nazionale nord europeo
incluso le rappresentazioni diplomatiche
la politica agricola, la politica regionale
io ho finito il mio bilancio con 0,96%
cioè il mostro
e qui evidentemente
c'è stata una diseducazione decennale
che poi ha dato i frutti del Brexit
questo è quello che io penso
accordi, TTP Canada
quello del Canada lasciamo un po' in disparte
per darsi che va davanti
il TTP, il Pacifico, il TTIP atlantico
e l'efficio che va davanti
compreso quello Pacifico
perché è significativo
Obama lo appoggia e i due candidati ne sono contro
perché chi va alle elezioni
oggi tiene conto di una generale tendenza
anti free trade
inarrestabile
per cui è un grave problema per il mondo
perché il free trade ha dato
a 2 miliardi di persone una vita decente
non è che ci ha provocato un sacco di problemi
a noi ma
dovrebbe andare avanti il gestito etc
ma ormai siamo in una situazione politica
per cui con la frammentazione di tutte
non solo dei partiti ma anche delle rappresentazioni
di interessi c'è sempre qualcuno
a cui non piace un pezzo di free trade generale
ai coltivatori diretti non piace
una parte ai farmaci
ai ricercatori l'altra
per cui in una società così complessa è sempre più difficile
concludere i trattati generali
o dovremmo trattare
lavorare su trattati con singoli paesi
e qui allora quello con Canada
può fare qualche progresso
anche se ci sono alcuni punti sottovii
oppure su singoli settori
il futuro a mio parere va in questa direzione
trattati generali con un nuovo umore politico
non se ne riescono più a fare
l'Africa in Cina
è una semplicità estrema
la Cina trova nell'Africa quello di cui ha bisogno
ha un miliardo di 300 milioni di abitanti
20% della popolazione del mondo
7% delle terre arate
e quello trova il cibo
non ha petrolio trova l'energia
ha poche materie prime rispetto alle città
e trova le materie prime e le trova in Africa
e in America Latina
e la fa l'Africa
qui c'è una grande differenza
che mentre noi non facciamo politica per Africa
a livello europeo
ma politica frammentata
quando c'era un problema africano
la commissione anche in miei tempi
quindi ne prendo la mia responsabilità
ma affidava il capofilo
all'ex paese coloniale
se non altro perché conosceva mai il paese
se c'era un problema in costa d'Avorio
era il commissario francese
che faceva l'istruzione Serin Zimbauer
era quello britannico
gli interessi sono assolutamente separati
l'unico paese che ha impostato i suoi interessi africani
in un modo continentale è la Cina
la Cina ha relazioni diplomatiche
con 51 paesi su 54
e avere
aperture diplomatiche
per la Cina voleva dire fare chiudere
l'ambasciata di Taiwan
a tutti questi paesi
cioè fare una scelta politica forte
e ha sempre fatto questo
ponendo una politica non condizionata
di aiuti
fregava assolutamente di niente sul dittatore
ma seguendola però molto da vicino
su come veniva spesa
e soprattutto
richiamo quello che ho detto prima
con emigranti che andavano a lavorare
e quindi eseguendo i lavori
in tempi rapidissimi
dando quindi un'idea di efficienza
per cui appunto come dicevo prima
i bootflicks, molti leader africani
dicevano che i cinesi mi rompono le scottele
però fanno le ferrovie
questo era l'atteggiamento
e poi si sono create anche
certualmente, teniamoci, i cinesi picchiano duro
le tensioni nelle miniere
l'uso della mano d'opera locale
nell'Africa nera
non si verifica mai
quell'aspetto dei matrimoni misti
di cui ho parlato prima
con tutta una serie di problemi molto gravi
ma con una politica che alla fine
viene ritenuta più concludente
dal punto di vista dell'interesse
dell'interesse del paese
questo è delle cose
allora cosa dobbiamo fare, dobbiamo fare una politica europea
in cui io penso che l'idea
di una politica africa e italiana isolata per l'Africa
così trovi
molti limiti
e noi possiamo fare una politica
per il coro d'Africa
o per la Libia o per un pezzettino di questi
ma con delle limiti
guardate la guerra di Libia
è un simbolo
del disfaccimento europeo
io all'inizio
quando iniziò
la guerra total
per via della benzina
non per via dell'universalità
poi andando successivamente
delegati in Africa
mi sono accorto che il discorso era molto più profondo
cioè
Gaddafi non solo era stato un dittatore
che è duro
ma tutta la prima fase del suo
potere
era un trouble maker
faceva casino dappertutto
poi è arrivato
un certo momento
che si è stancato
visto che aveva pochi risultati
e dal momento in cui
l'ho invitata a Bruxelles
con una reazione durissima
durato un mese solo
degli americani e degli inglesi
perché il mese dopo al vertice del Cairo
dovevo aspettare lungamente per vedere Gaddafi
perché c'erano tutti gli americani e gli inglesi in fila
e c'era il primo ministro irlandese
che tornò da un colloquio orgoglioso
perché aveva venduto tanta carne
bovina naturalmente
però ecco qui
viene il fatto chiave
da quel momento Gaddafi
ha voluto essere il re dell'Africa
lo esprimo in termini
e ha cominciato a investire massicciamente
in tutta l'Africa subsariana
e questo per la Francia
è un grande problema
addirittura c'è la leggenda che avesse preparato
dei soldi e dell'oro
per far sostituire
il franco francese
con un franco africano
che ho sentito da fonti americane
non le so assolutamente analizzare
se sono vero o meno
ma invece quello che ho visibilmente visto
questa politica libica
che rompeva gli equilibri
del subsara francese
e queste sono cose
in un paese voi vedete che
i libidori del patume
i trasformatori dell'elettricità
gli alberghi, le scuole, le università
è tutto francese no?
e allora il problema diventa
un problema molto complicato
ecco mi fermo qui
grazie
l'auspicio è che questa sia
la prima
di una serie di presenze
del Presidente Prodi qui da noi
all'interno dell'istituzione
e in particolare per i temi
che più da vicino riguardano
le scienze politiche e sociali
ma allargandoci benevolmente
per raccogliere tutte le competenze
che questa istituzione racchiude
penso di poter ringraziare a nome anche dell'istituzione
e invitare non solo il Presidente
ma gli ospiti e gli allievi studenti del MIS