Sottotitoli creati dalla comunità Amara.org
Anna Maria Luisa è responsabile per la vasta collezione di arti medici che sono ora, oggi, nel palazzo e nella galleria di Florence.
Without this woman Florence wouldn't be Florence.
And so I'm very glad because also in the present, not also in the past, we search to improve this attention.
Our administration, for example, is the first one who has made it by the 50% of women for the first time in the history of Florence.
Unfortunately the mayor is a man, but nobody is perfect.
I will remain a man, the mayor will change in the future.
And I am very honored also because this place is a particular place not only for the history, but for the future.
If I think about the fourth world conference, a woman in Beijing, I was very impressed by a speech of a woman who will always be in our hearts, Benazir Bhutto.
Benazir Bhutto defined empowerment as the right to be independent, to be educated, to have choices in life.
Empowerment is the right to have the opportunity to select a productive career, to own property, to participate in business, to flourish in the marketplace.
Flourish is a very important word in Florence.
We must shape a world free from exploitation and maltreatment of women.
A world in which women have opportunities to rise to the highest level in politics, business, diplomacy and other spheres of life.
Also in the speech of Hillary Clinton, we can search the expression flourish.
If women are healthy and educated, their families will flourish.
If women are free from violence, their families will flourish.
If women have a chance to work and earn as full and equal partners in society, their families will flourish.
When families flourish, communities and the nations will flourish.
So I was very impressed because my city is Florence, the city of the flower.
I hope in the city of the flower your wishes, your hopes.
Let me say our wishes, our hopes may flourish.
Thank you for coming. Enjoy your stay.