E ora è un onore, a seconda della gente del Protectorate di Albania,
di dare la piazza all'italiano prime ministero e protettore del nostro paese, Giorgio Melone.
Buongiorno a tutti, amici.
Mi chiedo di dire grazie a Eddie, non per essere un protectorate,
ma per la sua ospitalità calda e il suo sommet.
E anche per farmi sentire molto giovane di nuovo con quel video che ha mostrato in l'inaugurazione.
E voglio anche congratulare Eddie per la sua reelezione assolutamente inespettata
come leader del governo albanese.
Sono felice che l'Europa continui a raccontare il suo spirito e la sua determinazione.
Albania chiede alla comunità politica europea per la prima volta,
la valgo particolarmente significativa, non solo per questa nazione, ma per tutti noi.
Ho sempre considerato l'identità europea come un fattore,
fondamentale dalla storia, anche prima della geografia.
Un concetto che è più difficile di incontrare in una definizione che di capire con l'impulso.
Albania è ovviamente l'Europa, come l'Italia, la Serbia o la Norvega,
non importa se sono parte di questa o quella organizzazione.
Questo è il motivo per cui sono sempre felice quando qualcuno tenta di raccogliere il diritto
per decidere chi è l'Europa e chi non è.
Tra gli Stati che sono qui oggi, alcuni hanno deciso di non ingiuntare all'Europa,
altri sono ispirati a essere parte.
Inoltre, i Stati che sono qui oggi sono più o meno europei,
ma l'Europa è oggi la casa di Sandro Comandante,
per raggiungere il riuscito di unificatione europea,
attenzione ai mongoli, a persone che possono differenziare tra l'altro,
ma sono parte di un'altra, come le mani diverse di una mano.
Le persone che hanno battuto oltre i secoli sono in realtà una sola persona.
Inoltre, per questo motivo, sono qui oggi per fare un passo avanti
nel processo storico di unificare l'Europa,
perché se vogliamo costruire una nuova Europa in un nuovo mondo,
non possiamo immaginare di farlo senza i balcani stessi,
senza le loro persone, senza le loro identità e le loro background storiche.
I balcani stessi non sovrapponono il finger dell'Europa o del nostro continente.
Siamo al very heart del nostro continente.
Siamo la regione bridge tra l'est e l'est,
tra quello che St. John Paul II ha voluto chiamare i due lunghi d'Europa.
Per questo motivo, l'Italia è committa in Brasile
a servire un approccio strategico per i balcani stessi
per prendere into due account despite the complex challenges posed by the region.
They need to provide these countries with a clear EU integration perspective.
Of course, enlargement involves new challenges,
but I am convinced that the European integration of Western Balkans
as well as towards the East is also strategic investment on Europe's own security,
even more so in light of what is happening on our borders.
We live in an extremely interconnected world.
Our destiny is interdependence is fact.
What happens on European's eastern borders
is connected with what happens on its Mediterranean borders and vice versa.
The wound that Russia's wars of aggression against Ukraine has inflicted
on the rules-based international system still produces the stabilizing effects
well beyond the war borders and, like a domino,
this contributes to reigniting or detonating other crisis hotbeds, crisis hotbeds.
We have witnessed this in the Middle East and not only there.
That is why we will continue to stand by Ukraine
and to strive for this war to immediately come to an end
because our security and freedom depend on restoring the force of law
over the law of the strongest.
And speaking of Europe and freedom,
I believe it is nothing more European than a people willing to risk everything
to defend its own freedom and independence.
Every day the heroism and tenacity of the Ukrainian people reminds us
what Europe is and what the deepest aspect of our common identity is, freedom.
We defend our freedom and we want peace.
Volodymyr and the Ukrainian people want peace and we newly witnessed it yesterday.
The world saw who was really willing to sit at a negotiation table and who was not.
And this shows also with respect to certain propaganda
who looks for peace and who doesn't.
At the same time we must not interpret what happened yesterday as a setback
and throw in the towel.
Instead we must insist with determination to finally achieve
an unconditioned ceasefire and a true peace agreement
with serious security guarantees for Ukraine
and we are absolutely ready to do what is needed to reach this goal.
However, colleagues, I do agree with many things that Eddie said in his speech,
but building a new Europe in a new world as advocated by this session means,
in my opinion, before talking about what we have to do,
starting from our very foundations and reflecting mainly on who we are.
None of us is interested in strengthening any form of union amongst European states,
if not for protecting what we are and what we want to continue to be in the coming decades
and centuries in such a fast-changing world.
Because if Europe sometimes proves unable to face the great challenges,
it is no one else's fault.
It is our responsibility.
And it is up to us to choose whether to go along a decline or instead fight it.
And if we decide to fight it, first of all, we need to regain awareness,
which is mainly awareness of who we are, what the European civilization is,
of the great achievements it has accomplished across the history of humankind.
A synthesis of values resulting from the encounter between Greek philosophy,
Roman law, Christian humanism, a synthesis of values that allow the European civilization
to conceive a world in which the person's central life is sacred and human beings are free
and equal.
A civilization that respects the identities of the others without denying its own
and that builds peace where instead others see destruction.
We are this.
We are this before everything.
And I think we have, first of all, to remember it every day
if we want to build a Europe up to the role received from history.
Thank you.