e, Chris, abbiamo creato un clima di Pontignano dentro la Commissione europea,
che è abbastanza un raggiungimento.
Allora, cercherò di rispondere alla vostra questione, Chris,
non referendo quasi a tutto al campo in cui ho cercato di essere attivo,
ma cercherò di rispondere in termini più generali.
Allora, se guardiamo i ultimi 10 anni,
l'Europa, che è spesso trattata di non aver messo in posto sufficienti reformi strutturali,
e possiamo tutti sbagliare su questo,
ha messo in posto 4 strutturali strutturali storiche di se stessa.
È molto conosciuto che, solo in 10 anni,
ci sia stato l'accedimento del mercato singolo,
del mercato singolo, dell'enlargimento e della Costituzione.
Questo è molto conosciuto, ma è troppo facilmente dimenticato.
E non dovremmo dimenticare che ogni esercizio di questi obiettivi
è stato pronunciato come quasi impossibile
da molto dell'intelligenza in Europa,
negli Stati Uniti e altrimenti,
forse un o due anni prima,
che è passato in posto punctuale.
Ora, credo che sia anche normalmente sbagliato
quanto queste 4 cose
possano avere una relazione con il grande problema dell'economia europea
e la sua competitività.
E' in più di nessun dubbio che l'Europa non presta bene
dal punto di vista della competitività,
ma vorrei fare il punto che,
è che questo possa essere in parte a causa
della concentrazione delle energie politiche
su questi 4 obiettivi,
ma che, allo stesso tempo,
avendo trasformato l'Europa in questo modo,
per esempio,
rendendo l'Europa un po' più simile all'U.S. come un'entità,
può solo aiutare la crescita futuro e la competitività in Europa.
È chiaro, per esempio,
che la singola correnza
ha portato con la correnza
da indisciplina fiscale a disciplina fiscale.
È ben possibile che, nel termine sottile,
questo possa aver portato una crescita più bassa,
ma credo che tutti aggrediremmo
che questo sia un prequisito sottile per il sviluppo futuro.
Anche la costituzione,
solo il mercato, solo la correnza, l'enlargimento,
la costituzione, anche la costituzione.
Giuliano, che è la relazione
tra la costituzione e la competitività?
Non c'è una relazione.
Ma è chiaro a tutti
che una compagnia non può essere competitiva
se ha un processo di decisione veloce e incerta.
Questo non è molto diverso per la nostra nazione
o per un set di nazioni.
A livello che la costituzione
porti un processo di decisione
più racionali e veloci,
credo che questo aiuterà la competitività d'Europa.
Quindi, quando vedremo
i ultimi 10 anni della storia europea,
credo che confermerà che l'Europa
non ha fatto abbastanza bene
dal punto di vista della performance economica,
ma probabilmente abbastanza la base
per una performance economica più soddisfatto
dal punto di vista dell'Europa.
È chiaro, però,
che non possiamo solo restare là
e aspettare questa struttura fondamentale
di trasformazione per portare a livello
la dividenza in termini di crescita più alta
e dell'implicamento e della competitività.
Ci sono le politiche necessarie.
E qui, Chris,
per rispondere alla vostra domanda
o al titolo di questa sessione,
i successi e i setbacki in Europa
over the past 10 years,
what I would regard as a major problem
which has emerged more and more clearly
is a decoupling.
A decoupling by member state
between two things.
The willingness to accept
a somewhat greater integration and coordination
Europe-wise,
selectively, without exceeding,
with greater attention paid at the same time
also to subsidiarity,
but to accept some greater coordination
in certain area, one prerequisite,
and the other one to be serious and tough
in terms of domestic economic reforms.
To simplify things exceedingly,
I believe that we have seen
an increasing decoupling in Europe
between these two necessary prerequisites,
in my view,
in order to have a competitive Europe,
not just an internal competition
between one and the other.
To simplify things,
and at the risk of being unjust,
certainly Germany and France
have once again displayed
a greater willingness to accept coordination,
including in the constitutional debate,
than, say, the UK or Spain.
At the same time, there have been
pretty recalcitrant in terms of
domestic economic reforms.
I believe we need both things
if we want a competitive Europe,
but there has been this increasingly
visible decoupling.
Now, I think we should ask ourselves
the question, is there an inherent conflict
between these two attitudes,
both of which, in my view,
are necessary for a competitive Europe?
I believe there is not inherent conflict.
Of course, as I said,
a great deal of attention,
and here we can only learn from the UK,
has to be paid to subsidiarity.
And in certain areas,
we have in the last ten years
brought about greater coordination,
but some devolution to the national authorities.
I can here mention perhaps
the reform in the area of competition.
But I don't see that
there is an inherent conflict
between these two attitudes.
And I must say, Italy, for one,
as I see it,
has been rather more close
to Germany and France
in terms of acceptance
of a greater degree of coordination,
and, at least in principle,
but also with some implementations
ready towards economic reforms domestically.
Now, in this context,
I see a very substantial hope
in the enlargement.
We normally consider
the effects of enlargement
at constant policies.
Enlargement will not
keep policies constant.
Enlargement will transform
the policy trade-offs, I believe.
And what I see
in the new member states,
most of them, all of them,
is at the same time the willingness
to have greater coordination
and, for sure, a strong
central enforcer of the rule
of the European Commission
and a tough policy of domestic
economic reform.
And here, again, to make one
reference to Italy,
with all the abstraction
of these geometrical discussions
about foreign politics,
I believe that a country like Italy,
with a government like the present
government of Italy,
should perhaps even intensify
the efforts to become a reference point
without discarding
other friendships and alliances
for this group
of small
and or new
member states, which are really
rejuvenating the European Union.
My time is almost over.
One
important
setback
or insufficient progress
is the explanation
of Europe to Europe's citizens,
in particular
to the younger generations.
And here I see,
frankly, a monumental paradox.
Why?
We all know that the younger generations
lose interest and love
for Europe, especially because
they have not lived through the things
that Europe has been able to remove.
And at the same
time, if we think of it, Europe
is the key ally
of the future generations.
Giuliano referred to
the dimension of the future, as I
see it.
Europe is the main driver,
the main introducer
of a reference to the future
in our societies and in our debates,
both in terms of
forcing us all to consider
the future and in terms
of forcing
us to respect the future,
consider the future. What would have
been in each of our countries
the policies, the
politics, if we had not
had the target of 1993
for the single market,
of 1997, to bring down
the deficit?
Now Lisbon is a bit weak because it
does not crucify
countries similarly
effectively to that.
So if there has been a reference to the
future, it has been most of the times
brought by what the collective
wisdom of member states and the commission
have decided
should be a future
reference for Europe.
And it has forced
countries and societies to
respect the future.
And really,
many of our countries
were running with
a beatitude of
unawareness, deficits of
12-15% of GDP
without there being any debate.
This was so at the beginning
of the last ten years, Chris.
Now we make
fights
about whether it is 2.9
or 3.1.
But the substantial effect of
Europe is that it has forced
upon domestic political
processes the respect for our
children, for the future
generations, not to have
them born with the burden
on their shoulders of the public debt.
So I think
that it should be possible, and
I'm delighted that President Barroso
has assigned a special responsibility
to Vice President Marco
Wallstrom to make an effort to
explain Europe. I think that those
to whom we find
it most difficult to transfer
the message of Europe, that is
the younger generations, are really those
which we should be able to
mobilize. Final note,
I think in ten years
the relevance of the commission
for all its weaknesses
has increased.
May I conclude with
a personal
reference here. Ten years
ago, believe it or not,
when I was first appointed to Brussels,
Italian journalists,
non-Italian journalists,
were totally uninterested in
my person.
It genuinely asked me
the question, but Professor,
why on Earth, on Earth
have you accepted to become
European Commission?
Well, last July
I had at least the great satisfaction
that nobody asked
me, in Italy or elsewhere,
Professor, why do you appear
not entirely happy of not being
able to continue to work
at the core of the European
process? Thank you, Chris.
The Council of Côme, intent on
burying German sovereignty,
there was Monsieur Mitterrand,
there was Jacques Delors,
and that they had a vision of
Europe and they were able to
explain it to people and they
were able to infuse people.
And that today the
generation of political leaders
have no vision,
all have
an existential problem
with countries
membership of the European Union.
I wonder if you think
that is true
and I'd be very interested
in your reflections on the other
issue as well.
Mario, would you like to start?
I think we should try to create
enthusiasm through concrete
facts.
And I believe that
both your questions, Chris,
are linked.
Can I start from the last one?
Conventional narrative about Europe.
I think that Mitterrand
called Delors era
was a great one.
But I think
it was largely responsible
for some of the subsequently
intervened problems.
Many of the things
that Neil has done
and talked about this evening
are
related remedies
to an excess
of vision relative
to administration.
And this has contributed
to impoverishing the vision
about Europe in our
citizens.
So I spoke earlier of a decoupling.
I think here there is another decoupling.
I think we should try to bring
vision and administration hand in hand.
Maybe I'm too pragmatic.
Maybe I'm too British. I'm sorry for that.
But, you know,
having been in charge of the single market
first and competition, then
how can one avoid
these influences?
And this links
back to the issue of explanation.
When will we be able to
bring to European citizens the notion
that the commission
employs a staff which is
smaller than the
city of Rotterdam does?
And one third of it
is related to translations
and interpretations.
So I think there is
a closer
link between vision and
administration than we
normally see. As to your first
question, is there or not
still an ideological divide?
Well, here I have
a personal, very strong
conviction. I think it's
profoundly wrong
to reason in the following way.
Low turn-out
rates to the European elections,
which is a fact.
Hence there is a
crisis in the politics
of Europe. Hence
let's try to make the politics
of Europe as similar as
possible to national politics.
In my view,
the crisis is a much wider
one of the political
process and of the democratic
process of
participation to the elections
at the national level as well
as the European level.
And I'm glad that the
Constitution did not go as far
as many would have liked it
to go in terms of
mimicking the play of
domestic politics.
I think that
the European Commission
of course
should have a president
politically connotated
with some involvement
of the European Parliament
in the selection of the president,
but I think
it would be the end
of the European construction
if we had, as many
would like to see, a commission
that is an executive, which is
a centre left one or a centre
right one. Can you just
imagine what the reaction
in the different member states, depending
on their current political majorities,
would be to decisions of enforcing
the law in that member state if
the colour of the commission is different from
the one of the member state?
So, I think it would be a
profound mistake.
Does this mean that
the European Commission is not a political body?
No, in my view.
But in a sense, it is
the party of integration,
which can have more
right-wing, more left-wing connotations.
I think it's
very important to have had
an input. I mean,
I think one of the problems of
some
rights in our member
states recently
arriving to power
is the erroneous belief that
because there was
a predominantly
majority of the left in the European
Council in a previous
age, then the European Union
is a product of the left.
I think that much of the European Union
is a product of
conservative thinking.
The single
market is largely the product of
Mr. Thatcher. The single
currency is largely
the product,
political speaking, Chancellor Call.
And I
love it when
I see in the Commission
that we have
different positions not
based on affinity
to this or that political family.
But if anything, or
flag, if anything, more linked
to the portfolio for which
we are responsible, which is
a logical, a rational
assignment of responsibility.
So I'm sure I did not
answer to your question.
Maybe I used enthusiasm after
having said that we should drop it.
But in terms of
ideological divide and the political
play at the European Union
level, I firmly believe
that the biggest mistake would
be to
just to try
to make it identical to the domestic level.
And of course here too explanation
is important. The commissioners
are faceless Eurocrats.
Of course we are faceless.
Of course we are Eurocrats.
But we lack
legitimacy.
Mention to me
one national government in
Europe, not the US,
where ministers,
if I can for a second,
presumptuously assimilate commissioners
to ministers,
undergo an individual
written and oral scrutiny
by the parliament. Of course
one can say that there has
been before
that a parliamentary
election, but we know this is not
the case for all ministers.
And at any rate they were not
elected to be ministers.
They have not gone through this individual
scrutiny.
This is again one myth
that obviously we have not been able
to dispel.
And it's ludicrous to see
people still convinced that the European
parliament lacks any
power when on the 15th
of March, the edes of March
of 1999,
Neil,
myself and other
18 colleagues
went back home
at midnight as
resigned commissioners. By the way
I was very much impressed
that that evening
for the first time I saw a
30 minutes cover.
Thanks. Thank you.
Mario.
I thought the question was to Neil.
Mario,
you will give the same answer
in a 30 minutes.
Perfect substitutability.
Well,
Minister Baldassari,
the European model
is for one generation.
My view is that
the inertial
European model, the
de facto configuration in most
of our member states, would be
for one generation.
The premium to the present relative
to the future. It is the effort
of the European Union to persuade
member states
to modify their
de facto model into one
which pays more attention to the future.
And
in this abstract
and so pleasant
academic environment
in which we find ourselves this evening
of course the future
does bring us to the notion
of investment
and therefore to the metal
which you reminded
linking that metal
to a rule
have not mentioned
that rule now.
There is no question that in economic
terms you know this
better than anybody else.
What is public
or private expenditure
for the future is more worthwhile
than what is public
or private consumption.
But as you said yourself
it's difficult then to identify
what precisely is investment.
And I was
struck by a comment of our colleague
Joachim Ammunia at a recent
seminar in Italy
where six members
of the Italian government were present
and Ammunia afterwards
noted that each of the
minister had excellent
reasons to say
that his
expenditure
I was going to say his or her
but minister Moratti was not there on this occasion
but probably with
very good justification
she would say the same.
So that's why
but so
just a reference
to the debate
Neil and I and others had when
the stability pact was created
my position in the commission
in 1997 was
that we should pay attention
to this distinction but we
should also rush up to establish
the methodology, the verification
to assess
what is what.
Very last question.
Perhaps
you can be quite brief.
Very short.
Mario Monti
said that