Il Consiglio della Diplomacia di Plenipotenzialità degli Stati Uniti
sulla creazione di un Corpo Criminale Internazionale.
Noi continueremo, questo mattino, ad ascoltare le declarazioni generali.
Ci sono 20 representanti del Stato partecipando a inscrivere su la lista di oratori per questo
mattino.
Poi, dobbiamo dare la parola ai representanti delle organizzazioni intergovernmentali e
delle organizzazioni non governamentali.
In questo modo, abbiamo deciso prima che tutte le declarazioni generali di questo mattino
devono essere realizzate all'interno del tempo previsto.
Dobbiamo utilizzare il nostro tempo efficatamente e, soprattutto, dobbiamo abbracciare bene
il vostro telefono portabile.
Grazie.
Avant de donner la parole au distingué représentant de l'Italie, puisse demander
au prochain orateur, le distinguées représentantes de la Slovakie, de bien vouloir prendre place
au siège réservé près du podium.
Cha orateur doit se limiter à 7 minutes.
Je prie de respecter ce limite.
Allora, andiamo a cominciare.
E dobbiamo dare la parola al distingué rappresentante dell'Italie.
E io prendo il rappresentante della Slovakie che prende la posizione al siège.
A sinistra.
A sinistra del siège riservé.
Mr. Chairman, distinguished delegates, this diplomatic conference marks the final stage
in a process that began in the wake of the Second World War to institute a permanent
international criminal court.
It has been a long and gruelling path fraught with so many lost opportunities and marred
by tragedies that have affected the whole of humanity.
Rome is about to be the venue for a new step forward towards the acknowledgement of the
respect due to human dignity and its effective protection, as it was in 1950 when the European
Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms was signed here.
Italy has long stood by those wishing to codify new rules for international coexistence and
to guarantee compliance with them through appropriate instruments.
For Italy, which is honoured to be hosting so many distinguished delegations, the establishment
of the International Criminal Court is a top priority.
We believe that we can contribute to it, drawing on Italy's centuries-old judicial tradition,
her campaigns on civil issues and her public opinion, which is expecting a reaction to
the many intolerable violations of human rights, and the horrors and hardships we have been
witnessing to often as onlookers in recent years.
Violence, grievous misdeeds and harassment perpetrated against individuals and whole
peoples are still in the conscience of our societies.
They stand as a warning to us all.
Fresh outbreaks of criminal deeds, which we believe to belong to the distant past, are
making it all the more necessary, urgent, to institute an international criminal court.
What our consciences and common sense demand is that we should put in place instruments
that we will be able to prevent and mete out punishment for the most alteration crimes
against international law, so that even when all the essential values are swept aside by
war, the duties demanded by human solidarities are not ignored, so that we make it utterly
clear to all that even in war, conduct is subject to rules and penalties.
Leaving crimes against humanity unpunished would signify the failure of the great efforts
that have been deployed since 1948 to translate solemn international declarations of principle
into provisions of international criminal law.
Ever since that time, the proliferation of so many conventions and declarations of rights
has stood in sinister and dramatic contrast to the proven inability to protect and safeguard
the primary and most elementary rights of all, that is, the right of every human being
to life and security.
It is not enough for the international community to reach agreement on the conduct constituting
international criminal offences, and authority is also necessary to prosecute them.
The only way to prevent the likelihood of collective repression and to foster reconciliation
is to institute an effective system to prosecute and convict the individuals who perpetrate
these crimes.
The court will not judge only in the name of the victors, and neither will the court be
a tribunal occasionally set up in response to the wave of indignation against crimes
that are committed from time to time.
It must be a strong institution, with all the indispensable features needed to guarantee
its credibility, with very broad participation to make its statute universal.
It must be a court that is devoid of partisan pressure, independent, impartial, based on
the principles of the right to fair trial and the right to judicial defense.
The court must effectively complement national courts.
No doubt the paramount roles of the domestic courts.
However, the international court must be given a jurisdiction to take cognizance in
cases where domestic courts are either unwilling or unable to act effectively and appropriately
and thereby bridge the void that this would create.
From a substantive viewpoint, it is crucially important to identify the crimes falling within
the jurisdiction of the court.
We share the view that it would be better to limit its jurisdiction to the most high
nose crimes committed in the context of an armed conflict, whether international or not.
Notwithstanding that it is the United Nations Security Council which retains responsibility
to ascertain aggression, the court should also be empowered to prosecute the crime of
aggression.
Failure to include this crime within the court's remit would deprive the new institution
of one of its primary functions.
In more general terms, the role and the specific peacekeeping and international security responsibilities
vested in the Security Council must be safeguarded.
For this reason, a solution must be found which will balance relations between the
Security Council and the court, ensuring that it can perform its judicial functions
in total independence and without hindrance.
An independent prosecutor must not only be empowered to institute proceedings when individual
States or the Security Council reports a crime, but also to take the initiative to
start the investigation independently.
Moreover, the credibility of an international criminal court will depend primarily on the
prior acceptance of its jurisdiction and not to its subsequent endorsement.
This makes it essential for the court's jurisdiction to be triggered automatically
and be imposed on States by virtue of accession to the States alone.
Without this kind of automatic jurisdiction, the court will remain an arbitration tribunal,
operating solely according to the contingent political will and will be substantially incapable
of preventing, pre-empting and punishing the crimes within its scope.
Every State party