provide also the basis for deepening of economic integration in other fields.
Second environment, it was emphasized that the EU and Russia have a lot of fundamental
interests in common in this field and much can be done also on the basis of the
existing international agreement and especially in the framework of the Nordic Dimension, the CFSP.
Third and last is armament. This could become a field of growing importance for
bilateral cooperation also in view of the EU declared intention to become more active
in dealing with the problem of the spread of weapons of mass destruction.
A final word, several participants have emphasized that quite important bridging role
can be played by the exceeding countries, the new member states, in view of strengthening
of EU-Russia cooperation by means of the links they have developed with Russia in the last decades.
Thanks.
Thank you very much, Latorre. I would like to ask if nobody is frustrated from these reports
of the different working parties. That means if they forgot perhaps an important point
which could have been discussed. Oh yes, but I will not open again the discussion about
this substance. It's only a form, it's time to one short compliment.
I just wanted to say that I never said that the southern countries are against democracy
or human rights. I think all these countries have already signed and ratified all the instruments
regarding to human rights. I just wanted to point out that democracy and human rights
should not be a kind of blackmail for our countries. Thank you very much.
Good. Well, I suppose that everybody agrees and I think my conclusion about these reports
is that we were able to give an answer to the basic question raised yesterday by Alvaro
Vasconcellos who was asking after the speeches of Mr. Amato and Elmar Brock if the convention
was not too inward looking exercise from the side of the EU and if the convention didn't
forget to think about the external identity. My impression after having heard these different
comments on the different external issues is that we have no substance, not only formal
decisions of the convention dealing with the decision making process, dealing with the
formal issues, we have now enough materials to develop an external identity in the different
fields which were approached this morning and which were very rich. I think it was also
very rich dealing with the different suggestions to the Italian presidency, everybody talked
about that and I think we are able to present now to this presidency a very rich program
of initiatives in the different directions which were underlined in the exposés.
I thank again the reporters, they had not a long time to prepare the report but they
did extraordinarily well and thank you again for your reports.
We will go over now to the second part of this and final part because it's already one
o'clock and we have still half an hour before finishing and I'm happy to give in the first
place the floor to President Lamberto Odini, former Prime Minister of Italy, thank you
again very much for having accepted our invitation and we are happy to hear your comments.
Well, thank you very much Mr. President. First I would like to congratulate Yai and
Professor Bonvicini to have organized this meeting on a vast agenda and wide ranging
discussions have taken place on so many subjects. Now Andrew Duff and myself have been members
of the European Convention but since on the results of the Convention you heard yesterday
Emma Brock and Giuliana Manto, I don't think we should enter into give our own judgment
on how we came out according to our own vision of the future of Europe and I think that Andrew
Duff and myself would want rather to look forward to the remaining work that the Convention
can make in the coming two weeks actually starting next week on the fundamental questions
of the policies including decision makings and what kind of criteria in decision making
especially expanding to the extent possible the qualified majority voting and Andrew I
listen with attention and the reports by the head of the groups, of the working groups
on these four subjects. I would like to make only a few comments if you allow me Mr. Chairman
both on the Mediterranean and especially the future of Iraq. I think there is less to
say perhaps in terms of comments concerning the other two groups. Now it was said and I
agree fully that the Barcelona process and the MEDA project should be revised, should
be revived and perhaps revised in light of developments. I think that is to be done.
We shouldn't forget that the Barcelona process main objective was to arrive at the free
trade area with this country by the year 2010 and now we hear that the United States is
expressed in the same view trying to organize in the course of time a free trade area for
the Mediterranean and the Middle East countries again in 10 years time. Now we do not know
what are the instruments that the United States intend to use to foster and this process
because it has not been specified whereas we do know which are the means that the European
Union has been using to try to bring about you know progress in the three different
fields and economy, the political area and the social progress that would lead therefore
also into the towards a free trade area by making these economies more competitive externally.
But why the MEDA and the Barcelona process did not progress as much as desired. Now I think
this may be a lesson to be useful also to the United States if it wants to help the
Mediterranean countries in their economic and social development. Now first I think
it is fair to say that the European Union has been slow in pushing forward the infrastructure
projects using the same criteria for that are applied to member countries and the same
demands, the same standards and that the European Union has required of member countries
the same have tried to apply to the Mediterranean countries where of course the conditions are
somewhat different. So there hasn't been much flexibility, the result is the gestation period
for infrastructure project has been extremely long. Second in the Mediterranean countries
there has always been let's say uneasiness on the expansion of NATO and also regional arrangements
that the European Union has made, Euromar, Euro4 during the years I have been foreign minister
have always been questioned and say why do you need all these arrangements? Why do you
need all these defense kind of instruments? Aren't these going to be a sort of a threat
vis-à-vis us? Now of course it is not but how to reassure these countries in this area
which I think is now even more fundamental question after the action of the United States
in Iraq, who is going to ensure security to the Mediterranean countries? We ought to think
about this. Indeed as part of the Barcelona process we worked for several years, more
than several years on a possible security agreement between the European Union and this
country so as to assure them that through the dialogue consultations and so on, on developments
of what Europe was doing that was not intended at all to constitute. So establishing better
cooperation in this field leading to a security agreement that has never been materialized.
Now this seems to me of a crucial question on security for these countries in the future.
Beyond what we can do, you know, ourselves. Now in terms of social progress and try to increase
and improve the understanding between these Mediterranean societies and European world,
the European countries, we had launched the idea of a Mediterranean TV, television,
in which there would be an exchange of programs between European programs that are devoted
to that part of the world and also programs and ideas coming from them that could be integrated
in Europe. Now also this project has not materialized. I must say that there were more fears
on the part of some of the Mediterranean countries than on the part of the European countries
because it would have meant for some of them to open up the kind of exposure to the public
of ways, way of life and the things that our society develops, you know, in terms of culture
in particular. So also these were the three reasons I think why the Barcelona process
and MEDA did not progress as much. Therefore let's revive and revise the Barcelona process.
I think that Europe can do much better in that part of the world in the Mediterranean
down to the Middle East than any other area or any other country. I'm ready to bet on this
that we can do much more for these countries in terms of bringing them closer.
I heard about association agreements. I think Europe should work on cooperation agreements
first of all. Some countries, Egypt and others, there is Tunisia, there is an association agreement
but it has been, you know, it will take time to develop but also that should be encouraged.
Now then policy for democratization of human rights, I think it has been said rightly,
this is not an exportable goods and in particular we should be sensitive to the maintenance
of regional stability and with economic growth will also the social and political development
I think will occur and this on the Mediterranean this would have been my comments.
Let's see in particular what the United States has in mind when he is proposing a free trade area
with these countries from the year 2012. See whether the US is in a position to do better than Europe
I doubt this but in any event let's hope that the United States also will make an effort
as much as Europe in favor of these countries. Now on the future of Iraq, I think there is a request
for a new European policy on Iraq and mention has been made to this excellent report by Solana
on fighting terrorism and also preventive action linking up hopefully well with the United States.
Now why it has not been possible so far to develop a single European policy on Iraq?
And we know the shambles in which the European countries found themselves and I think aside from
what has been said some countries may have had economic interest, I think that Europe
and this is the matter that links up to the convention does not have today an adequate mechanism
or an instrument, adequate and effective instrument for decision making.
And this is the key question. It has been an intergovernmental matter, foreign policy
and on which unanimity is required to say anything positive. I would like to say here once more
and I have said it elsewhere that in the five years that I have been foreign minister we discussed
the Middle East issue every month in the General Fair Council, it is to say the Council of Foreign Ministers.
And we all agreed around the table that of course we should foster the peace process
and being pleased to the region. But then when we started to decide