Non è una definizione, ma una regola, che dice che si può chiamare un paese una democrazia
quando ha cambiato il suo governo due volte per le elezioni.
Una volta non è abbastanza.
Abbiamo visto che un governo in potere, sia in principio, sia in advertenza,
può essere votato senza potere.
E quelli che vengono a rimanere il paese,
prendono una buona cura di non partire dalla stessa rotta in cui erano venuti.
Troppo, credo, che lo stabiliscono abbastanza bene.
La democrazia, in questo senso in cui ho definito,
ha una relazionazione molto limitata in storia umana e geografia.
In base, la forma di governo ha funzionato in una regione comparativamente piccola del mondo,
principalmente negli paesi inglesi.
E' stato trasplantato con successo intermitente
al continento dell'Europa,
dove il record è, diciamo, mixato,
e i prospetti anche.
Con in mente le vicissitudini della democrazia europea,
dovremmo essere più tolleranti
delle difficoltà che sono currentemente incontrate
da quelli che stanno cercando di introdurre la democrazia stile occidentale
in circostanti ancora più infamili.
Forse potrei fare il mio punto più chiaro con una semplice analogia
introdotta da un'altra invenzione della stessa fonte,
il gioco del football.
Il football è un gioco in cui due parti contengono
e fanno il loro piacere di vincere,
ma entrambi hanno gli stessi diritti,
entrambi operano sotto le stesse regole,
entrambi sanno che neanche vittoria e non vincere è finale,
e si incontrano per un piatto dopo.
Sì, forse uno potrebbe fare un'altra cosa,
che, anche se ci possono essere molti team,
il gioco è più efficace quando ci sono solo due
nel campo allo stesso tempo.
Andiamo a un altro termine importante,
che, di nuovo, è stato usato un numero di volte
nelle nostre discussioni qui,
il termine fondamentalismo.
Questo è un termine, la storia della quale è conosciuta,
il significato originale della quale è molto specifico.
Il nome fondamentalismo, il vero fondamentalismo,
non è soltanto esterno, è americano-protestante.
È stato usato prima, secondo le lexicografie,
in circa il 1920,
per designare alcune strade americane-protestanti
e per differenziarli
dalla strada principale delle strade protestanti.
Il nome viene da una serie di bokletti
pubblicati da queste strade,
da un clergyman da queste strade,
con la lettera generale, i fondamentali.
Una serie di bokletti chiamati fondamentali,
quindi i fondamentalisti,
quelli che credono su queste principali.
I fondamentalisti differono da la strada principale delle strade protestanti
e, dunque, altri cristiani,
su due punti maggiori.
La teologia liberale e il critico biblico.
Li hanno obbligato fortemente a entrambi.
Erano contro la teologia liberale in tutte le forme
e insistivano sulle textuali divinità
e inerranza della Bibbia.
Ora, in Irlanda,
sono stato accostumato a usare questo termo fondamentalismo
con una lunga range di applicazioni.
E può essere mislevo.
Sto parlando specificamente
di quello chiamato il fondamentalismo islamico.
La teologia liberale è stata un'issue nel passato tra gli islami.
Può essere ancora un'issue nel futuro tra gli islami.
Non è un'issue nel momento presente.
Non è quello a cui stanno parlando.
Per l'inerranza e la divinità della Bibbia
è una dogma basica.
La divinità del Coran,
una che è riconosciuta,
o almeno non è chiamata
da tutti gli islami,
nonostante per il loro credere,
il loro praticare,
o nemmeno acquiescente.
La differenza tra quelli che noi oggi
chiamiamo fondamentali islamici e altri islami
è qualcosa di molto diverso.
È la domanda, basicamente,
della natura islamica del Stato.
È una politica e, a un certo punto,
una differenza sociale.
Il loro movimento è una protesta
contro ciò che vedono
come la deislamizzazione
del Stato e della società
nei paesi islamici
sotto le influenze perniciose, alienanze
e infideli.
E il loro rimedio è la reislamizzazione
del Stato e della società,
in particolare,
con la reimposazione
dell'Islamo Sospetto,
della Sharia,
che gli islami credono
diventare divinissimi e ottenere.
Alcuni hanno protestato
contro l'uso di questo termine,
in particolare,
perché ha avuto
un elemento di pregiudizio,
in particolare,
perché ha avuto
un elemento di pregiudizio,
di condemnation.
In alcuni paesi,
il termine islamismo è usato
e quelli che professano
queste creazioni sono chiamati islamisti.
Questo, a me sembra,
è molto più pericoloso,
perché avrebbe impiato
che questo sia qualcosa di centrale
e tipico dell'islam,
che non è certamente.
Nel francese, il termine integrismo
è usato, in italiano
dico integrismo.
Queste sono di nuovo
termini cristiani westerni,
irrelevanti all'islam,
ma non voglio pronunciare
in francese o in italiano.
Ciò che mi sembra significativo
è che in anni recenti
il termine inglese, il termine
americano-protestante, il termine fondamentalismo
è stato letteralmente,
textualmente traslato in arabic
e persiano e turco
e, non dimenticare, in altre
lingue dell'islam e usato
per designare questi movimenti.
E se gli islamisti usano questo termine
per designare i movimenti islamici,
penso che avremo bisogno
di fare la stessa cosa
e non sentire l'imbarizio.
La mia quarta definizione
è la termina islamica.
È già stata
menzionata molte volte in questo
meeting, e ancora le certe
ambiguità che arrivano.
Per iniziare, c'è una cosa molto ovvia,
ovvia quando è menzionata,
ma non molte volte
osservata,
che è che usiamo in inglese e in altre
lingue, abbiamo già usato il termine
islamo in due sensi diversi.
Lo usiamo come l'equivalente
della cristianità,
cioè il nome di una religione,
e lo usiamo anche come l'equivalente del
cristianismo, cioè
di una civilizzazione, una cultura
storica, un fenomeno, una civilizzazione
che è cresciuta sotto l'egis
di quella religione. Non è necessario
di spiegare a questa audience
la differenza nel significato,
nel scopo tra i due
termini cristianità e cristianità,
è più difficile
spiegare e mantenere la differenza
tra questi due
differenti definizioni
o usaggi del
stesso termine islamo.
L'ultimo professore Marshall
Hodgson della Università di Chicago,
un grande scolaro su la storia islamica
e la civilizzazione,
che ha detto questa distinzione,
ha suggerito che useremo
il termine islamdom
come l'equivalente del cristianismo,
una buona suggerizione,
ma non ha mai accaduto,
e nessuno, inoltre i personali
disibili del prof. Hodgson
hanno mai usato questo termine in inglese,
non so quale l'equivalente
in altre lingue, esattamente
in turca, dove ci sono due
parole da distinguere,
ma non in arabica e altre lingue.
È molto difficile
generalizzare
l'islamo. Stiamo parlando, ricordate,
di più di 14 secoli di storia.
Stiamo parlando
di più di un milione di persone.
Stiamo parlando di 54
stati sovrapposti,
membri dell'organizzazione
dell'Islamo Congresso,
più grandi minorità musulmane
in Cina,
in India, e ora in crescendo
in l'Europa e
le America.
Inoltre,
bisogna fare l'attento.
Let me turn now
to the
relationship between religion
and political culture
and try to
establish some ground rules
which I will
follow in my discussion
of Islam and Islam's
relationship to liberalism,
to democracy, and more generally
to political culture.
In a sense,
the question
is Islam compatible
with liberal democracy
is part of a larger question.
Is religion compatible
with liberal democracy?
Here I think it may be useful
to make a basic distinction
which applies to all
religions. The distinction
between religion in the sense of
belief, conduct,
worship,
and religion in the
sense of an ideology of empowerment
and enforcement.
In this first sense,
religion as a system
of belief, of conduct,
and of worship, in that sense
there seems to me to be no
reason why
any religion in those
terms should be incompatible
with liberal democracy,
nor indeed with any form of government
that is not in itself
inherently evil.
Such have existed
as we know, as we were recently
reminded. In the other
sense, religion as
an ideology of empowerment, that
of course is another matter.
I think it may be useful
to point
to what seems to me
to be the main differences
between the Christian
Jewish and Islamic
approaches.
And I would like to do so
in terms of what, without intending any
disrespect, I would call the founding
myths of the three religions.
Moses,
you will recall, was not
permitted to enter the promised land.
And
the Hebrew Bible, the
Old Testament,
is dominated by the
two themes of
bondage and liberation
of exile and return.
Jesus was crucified
and his followers survived
as a persecuted minority
for centuries
before finally
converting the state
and inaugurating the processes of
the Christianization
of Rome, and some would add the Romanization
of Christ.
The founding
story of Islam is very different.
The Prophet Muhammad
conquered his promised land
and established a state,
a polity of which he was chief.
Not he, but some of his
enemies were put to death.
And his scripture
tells the story
first of a struggle
to attain power, and
then of the exercise of power.
Muhammad created the first
Muslim state in Medina
and he was the head of it.
And he did what heads of state do.
He dispensed
he promulgated
laws, he dispensed
justice, he collected taxes,
he made war,
he made peace. In other words, he acted
as a political sovereign.
And the
the record, the memories
of his sovereign acts as well as
of his prophetic mission
are part of the central
core of self awareness
of Muslims everywhere
in the world.
And that I think is a very
very important, indeed a
crucial difference
in the Muslim
attitude
to politics in general
and to the conduct of government in particular.
A subject which I should
add is much discussed
in Muslim religious
and legal literature.
There is
a Muslim political
culture.
Indeed, one may speak of
several Muslim political cultures.
If one wants to look
at the compatibility of Christianity
and democracy,
one has I think to take three or
perhaps more accurately four different
varieties. Again,
I am not concerned with
theological
or philosophical or theoretical
statements of any kind
on this particular point,
merely with the historical record.
If you look at the historical
record of the
attempts to run democratic societies
in countries of Orthodox,
of Catholic and of Protestant
Christianity, you would I think be able
to draw up an interesting comparative
table. I said
four rather than three.
The fourth I would call the
post-Christian society.
I would remind you
that secularism is a Christian notion.
Secularism
is a post-Christian
answer to a Christian
dilemma, one which
is posed in the Gospels,
the dilemma of God and Caesar
and which continued to haunt
Christians throughout the history of
Christianity.
That particular dilemma was not a problem
for Muslims. The very notion
of secularism,
of laity,
of totally alien.
Arabic is a Christian as well as
a Muslim language. There are large
words, large and important
Christian communities of Arabic
speech and a considerable Arabic
Christian literature.
So the Arabs did have an advantage
over the Persians and Turks and other peoples
in that they had a Christian vocabulary
available to them in their language.
So there was a word for secular
in Arabic. There was none
in Persian or Turkish. They had to invent
them.
Laity is again an alien
notion. The idea
that some things are
clerical, others are lay is a
Christian notion of very little relevance.
A point I think is very important
to emphasize
is that these three religions,
Judaism, Christianity,
Islam, are closely
related.
If one compares them with the
great religions of Asia, with
Buddhism, Hinduism,
the religions of the Far East, they
are as alike as peas in a pod.
From a larger
perspective, one would I say,
one might I say regard these
as variants of
the same basic religious tradition.
That is I think nowadays
partly at least recognized.
Several speakers in the
last couple of days have used the term
the Judeo-Christian tradition
or Judeo-Christian religion.
This is an old reality
but a very modern term.
Before the present century, it would have
been found offensive on both sides of the hyphen.
Nowadays
it's passed into common
usage on both sides
of the hyphen. One could of course
though one doesn't usually speak
with equal justification of a
Judeo-Islamic tradition.
Jewish life in the period between
the destruction of the ancient Jewish
polity and the creation of the modern
Jewish polity was passed
mainly in the lands of Christendom
and of Islam.
The Jewish experience outside
these two is insignificant.
And there is a
Judeo-Islamic tradition just
as there is a Judeo-Christian tradition.
One of the more interesting
things about the modern state of
Israel is that therefore the first
time in many centuries
the Judeo-Christian and the Judeo-Islamic
traditions meet
in the same state
and one sees the great
differences between them
almost a
laboratory controlled experiment
on the larger encounter of
Christendom and Islam.
This kinship
between Christianity and Islam and
Judaism
has made communication
possible.
We find for example in the Middle Ages
in Spain, in Sicily and elsewhere
Christians and Muslims engaging
in disputations,
theological disputations.
This was possible because both
were speaking the same language
figuratively as well as literally
talking about the same things.
Such a disputation would have
made impossible with a Hindu or a Buddhist
or a Confucian, there would have been no common
language.
When Christians and Muslims
denounced each other as infidels
each knew exactly what they meant
because they meant the same thing.
When Christians and Muslims said to
each other you are an unbeliever and you will
burn in hell, again
both understood what the other
meant because both meant precisely the same
thing. Their heavens are
somewhat different but their hells are almost
identical.
All that by way of
introduction to explain
some of the terms that I am using.
I want to turn now to a more
specific examination of Islam
in relation
to liberalism,
democracy, liberal democracy,
whatever and to consider
first those elements
in Islamic civilization, in Islamic
history which would militate
against the success
of democracy
in Islamic lands and then
since I prefer to end on an optimistic note
then those that
are more positive and more favourable.
The first and
most obvious one is the
unmistakable authoritarianism
of the Islamic
political tradition.
An authoritarianism which it shares
of course with most of Christendom
for most of Christian history
but which in the case of Islam
is almost completely
unrelieved.
This authoritarianism is both
historic and doctrinal.
If we look at the record of Muslim states
we find that authoritarian
rule is the norm.
If we look at the 54
Muslim states at the present time
the vast majority
are authoritarian in one
form or another.
Only one of them
remotely qualifies
as a democracy
by Huntington's definition
of having changed the government twice
by elections, that is the Turkish
Republic and that is
still a very troubled
democracy, although it does
change governments by elections.
There is also a
doctrinal authoritarianism
in the very notion
of holy law, of a divine
law, revealed,
formulated, promulgated
which regulates not
only those things which in
other religions might be regarded as
specifically religious but
also every aspect
of life
and more particularly
such things as marriage, divorce,
inheritance, family life
and the rest and of course
the conduct of the state.
That is not
very conducive to the development
of liberal institutions or democratic
ways. The earliest
description of England
that we have,
the earliest that is to say in any
detail, is a Muslim
from Lucknow who visited
England in 1798.
He was of Persian
background and wrote a book in Persian
a fascinating account of England and
France and
one of the places his hosts took him to
was the House of Commons
and this he tries to explain
to his readers back home.
He begins with a rather unflattering comparison.
He describes the two sides
of the house and says this
is like what one often sees in India
two trees
on opposite sides of the road both full of
parrots squawking at each other.
But then he goes on to explain what this is for
and he explains that
the poor benighted English
unlike the Muslims had never
accepted a divine law
and were therefore reduced to the expedient
of making their own laws
in accordance with the experience
of their judges and the necessities
of the moment, which he regards
obviously as a very
poor expedient
the people
who have denied themselves
this major benefit of divine
guidance.
That system you don't need
a legislative assembly
and that of course
has far reaching implications.
Another factor against linked to this
is the triumphalism.
The belief which Islam shares
with Christianity and as far as I know
with no other religion
are being the final possessor
of God's truth
which it is therefore their
sacred duty to bring to others.
This again makes
the interchange
and exchange
of democratic life more difficult.
One of the most serious
obstructions
is the position of women.
The first who raised this as a
major issue as far as I am aware
in a Muslim country was
Kamal Atatürk who again has
been mentioned several times at these
meetings, the founder
and first president
of the Turkish Republic,
an Ottoman Pasha and a military
general, an improbable feminist.
Nevertheless
he was the first to
proclaim the need for the emancipation
of women and the giving of political
rights to women.
He said
several times in a series of speeches
which he delivered in Anatolia in the early
1920s, he said
that our present task
is to catch up with the modern world.
We will not catch up with the modern
world if we only modernize half
the population.
A point which he understood
which many others still have
difficulty in understanding.
If we look at
the accounts of the West
written by Muslim travelers
this is the point on which
almost all seem
to agree the astonishing
to them freedom
accorded to women in Western
and Christian society.
Obviously the position of women
was very far from one of equality in the
West but it was incomparably
better than in most other parts of the world.
One that I find particularly
instructive
is a report from a Moroccan ambassador
in Spain in the late
17th century who comments
on the free and easy ways
of Spanish ladies and the lack
of manly jealousy of Spanish men.
This is Spain
of all places in the late
17th century.
His report on Spain doesn't tell us much
about Spain but he tells us quite a lot about
Morocco.
One of the major reasons
for the relative backwardness of
Islam is surely this
point. If a society
persists
in depriving itself of
the talents and services of half the population
and of entrusting
the nurture of the other half
to uneducated and down trodden
mothers, it will not be able
to keep up with the modern world
nor will it be able to operate any
kind of free
liberal democratic society.
This is increasingly understood
not always
not only I should say
by women, there are there as elsewhere
some women who prefer subordination
but I feel
myself that women who are
after all slightly more than half the population
may yet constitute
the best hope for liberal democracy
in the Islamic world.
I have already mentioned the lack of a legislative
power and therefore the
absence of any need
for a legislative assembly.
One could add
to that the difficulties
arising, this may seem
to you an odd formulation but I stand
by it, difficulties arising
at the present time from oil.
Oil has
enormously enriched some
Muslim governments.
It has freed them
from the need to raise taxes.
It has
freed them therefore from the need
to enter into a dialogue with their subjects.
It has provided
resources to maintain tyranny
at home and terrorism abroad
and in the long run it may well
prove to be a great curse
rather than a blessing.
And it is surely not without
significance that the most hopeful
signs of development
towards a freer society
occur in countries like
Tunisia and Jordan
and Turkey
which have no oil.
Another difficulty
is the absence in
Muslim law of what in
Roman law is called the legal
person.
There are only individuals.
There is no city, just an accumulation
of quarters and houses.
There is no abstract
legal, no corporate legal
entity.
This is an alien notion.
Therefore no form
of representation, no
form of majority decision.
In the past this didn't matter
but in trying to create
liberal democratic
institutions the absence
of such a tradition is
a serious obstacle.
It's an obstacle which is now
increasingly being overcome
as the modern economy
has created the need for
such institutions and such
laws.
Let me turn now to
what seem to me to be the factors
in Islam which
are conducive to the
development of liberal
democracy.
The first and most important of these
of the political
factors is the
Muslim doctrine of sovereignty.
This is a subject which is
widely discussed
by
jurists
and theologians in Islam
going back a very long way.
And the
supreme
institution of sovereignty is the
caliphate and there is much
discussion as to how one becomes caliph
and what one's duties are.
And a reading of these
texts makes it quite clear
that according to Muslim doctrine
the supreme sovereign office
is contractual
and consensual.
The caliph becomes
caliph by a contract
between him and his subjects.
A contract which imposes duties
as well as giving
rights to the ruler.
And it is consensual
in that it depends
on the consent of the ruled.
Now you might say this is
theoretical, this isn't how it actually happened.
This would be a
valid, though not entirely valid
criticism. In that generally
speaking certain minimal
norms were observed.
It is rare in Islamic history
that you find a complete despotism.
You find authoritarian
rule certainly, but
not unprincipled, unrestricted
despotic rule.
It is true that the law gives
authoritarian, gives autocratic powers
to the ruler, but it nevertheless
defines those powers.
An oft cited tradition
of the prophet, as well as
the Qur'an, Muslims believe in the traditions
of the prophet, these are sayings of the prophet
handed down by oral tradition.
A much quoted tradition
of the prophet is
there is no obedience in sin.
That means
that the duty of obedience
which the subject owes to the ruler
lapses when the ruler
orders something that is sinful.
And in that case
duty of obedience is replaced not
by a right of disobedience as in western
political thought, but by a duty
of disobedience.
Of course, there is no constitutional
procedure to decide
when a command is sinful.
That is left to
what we might tactfully call
the play of historical forces.
But the notion is there, the principle is there
and it has increasingly been
cited in modern times
by Muslim dissidents
of various kinds.
Some reference
was made this morning
to tolerance.
Professor Baudet
spoke very rightly
of the inadequacy of tolerance
as a notion in our time.
There is a letter
of George Washington
addressed to the leader of the Jewish community
in Newport, Rhode Island,
in which he says, I'm quoting from memory
but I think accurately,
he says, let us no longer speak of
toleration as if it were
by the indulgence of one group of people
that others enjoy
the exercise of their inherent
natural rights.
That is just over 200 years ago.
It is still not
generally accepted.
In saying that though, I think we should bear in mind
the very real tolerance
exercised by Muslim governments
at a time when this was very far from being
the norm.
The evolution of tolerance in
Christian societies was slow,
difficult, and reluctant.
Christian states
for many centuries found it difficult
to tolerate
not only other religions
but even deviant forms of their own.
In the medieval Muslim
states on the other hand, there was
an acceptance of diversity.
The Quran itself
says there is
no constraint in religion.
A German scholar has recently
argued that this is not a plea for
tolerance but an expression of resignation.
That is not how it was
generally understood.
There is also a saying attributed to
the prophet,
difference of opinion among my people
is a blessing from God.
Again,
an argument that diversity,
that pluralism are good things
in themselves.
This tolerance was of course limited.
It did not mean
as some modern apologists would have it
the granting of equal rights
of citizenship to non-Muslims.
That would have been seen
not as a merit
but as a dereliction of duty.
It is obviously absurd
to give equal rights
to those who reject it.
Nevertheless, there was
a very real tolerance
allowed to non-Muslim communities
and even a much more
searching test,
even deviant Muslim communities.
One does not find heresy hunts
and inquisitions
in Islamic history except
on very rare and exceptional
circumstances.
In most of the Muslim states,
Muslims of different branches
of the faith, Christians
of different churches, Jews
lived side by side.
Now, this was limited
tolerance, but it was
much more extensive
in one sense than what is
accorded to minorities of the present time.
And this gives rise
to one of the difficulties
of the accommodation
of Muslim minorities in
Christian or post-Christian states
in Europe and elsewhere at the present
time. Muslims
naturally expect
the same tolerance from
Christian governments as they
in the past gave to Christian
minorities in Muslim countries.
What they are in fact
getting is much more than that
but also much less
than that.
The status of a tolerated
minority under Muslim rule
carried with it a very
large measure of internal autonomy.
The Christian Ecclesiastical
Authorities had real and
enforceable jurisdiction
over the faithful.
They administered
their own laws and adjudicated
cases in their own tribunals.
The same was true of the Jews.
So that in the same street
if you had, shall we
say, a
Muslim, an Orthodox
Christian, a Catholic Christian and a
Jew, they would be subject to
four different systems of law.
If they died, their estates
would be divided according to four
different systems of inheritance law
and so on and so on. Even to
some extent criminal jurisdiction.
Let me quote one
example and an important one.
The question of polygamy
and concubinage.
Muslim law permits both polygamy
Jewish law in the Islamic lands,
though not in the Christian lands, permits
polygamy but not concubinage.
Christian law of all churches
at all times prohibits both polygamy
and concubinage.
It was therefore possible for
rabbinic and Christian
church authorities to
punish people and sometimes punish
them severely for offenses
which were not offenses at all
according to the law of the land, the
dominant community in the land
or breaches of the marriage laws.
They
controlled their own educational systems.
They had their own schools in which they taught
whatever they wanted to teach, provided
only that it was not subversive
and even that was not very rigorously
enforced.
One understands then
that Muslims who come to Europe
have a different notion
of minority rights
and minority status
and a different expectation.
These minorities in principle had no
political rights. They were not
supposed to participate in any way
in the conduct of government.
They were, with insignificant
exceptions, excluded from
the bearing of arms or from any form of
military service. In fact
they did sometimes participate in
politics but always in a relatively
subordinate capacity.
Here, the other side.
This
degree of tolerance
is of course no longer
acceptable by modern standards
and it broke down in the
19th century when
the non-Muslim subjects
of the Ottoman Empire and of other
Muslim states were no longer
satisfied with the
tolerated and subordinate
status accorded to them by the old
laws. They demanded
emancipation, they demanded equal
rights and so on. The old system
broke down. It has not
been adequately replaced.
Nevertheless, I think one should remember
that for a long time the
Muslim world was far more
tolerant than Christian
countries.
Nowadays we tend to
measure tolerance by
the movement of refugees
and intolerance rather
by the movement of refugees
from persecuting authorities
to free authorities.
We should bear in mind that until the
16th and 17th centuries the movement
of refugees was almost entirely
isolated from Christendom to Islam,
not only of Jews but even
of deviant Christians.
In 16th and 17th century
Istanbul, for example,
there were Protestants from Catholic
countries, Catholics from Protestant
countries and Jews from both
enjoying the relatively free
air of the Turkish Muslim capital.
The
economic point
is again I think an important one.
We tend nowadays to think of
the Islamic world as
irretrievably
feudal and therefore
opposed to free market
and other forms of capitalist
enterprise.
This is a
reversal of the historical
sequence.
In the West the classical sequence
is of course slavery,
feudalism,
capitalism.
But the Islamic history is not
Marxist. It doesn't follow the Marxist
rule.
It is of course slavery,
feudalism, capitalism.
But the Islamic history is not
Marxist. It doesn't follow the Marxist
rule.
These
matters were
debated intensely
and we have expressions of different
views.
The question, for example, of
price fixing versus
market forces
was hotly debated rather
than a thousand years ago in
Baghdad and Damascus and other cities of
the Middle East.
They quote a saying attributed to the
prophet, only God
can fix prices.
An eloquent
theological formulation of laisse
faire.
Another saying
is that he
who earns money is the friend of God.
Another saying
the honest
merchant who is killed
is a martyr.
In other words, counts as a martyr for the
faith.
The importance of the commercial
development of medieval
Islam is
recorded even by the vocabulary
which we use in European languages
at a time when feudal Europe
was a rather
impoverished primitive
outpost on the
wild northwest frontier
of the Islamic world.
Think, for example, of how many Muslim words,
how many Arabic or Persian words
there are in our commercial vocabulary.
Tariff
is Arabic.
The Italian dogana,
the French douane, come from the Spanish
adwana which come from the perso
Arabic diwan.
Czech is Persian and one could add
many others
which came from a
financially and economically
more advanced society
to a more primitive one.
The change there, as I said,
reversed the Marxist sequence,
a point which
Marx seems to have overlooked.
With
uncharacteristic humility, he did
recognize that the canonical
western sequence didn't apply
to other societies
and he met that by inventing
the Asiatic mode of production
which presumably covers everything
from Anatolia to Japan.
The feudal age
of the Islamic economy
has lasted for a very long time
but there again there is an earlier
tradition to which one can look
back with, I think,
elements
conducive to a better development.
Let me, before ending,
refer to
a