del Banco Centro europeo e un membro del gruppo del Banco per le Settilità internazionali,
come i diversi altri bancari e agenze internazionali.
Nel 2006 è stato electo Presidente di un gruppo di stabilità finanziaria.
Nel suo tempo sparo, se potete credere che ci sia nessuno,
è stato Trastee dell'Instituto per l'Advance Study in Princeton
e dell'Instituzione di Brookings, dove è ora Trastee di Emeritus.
E ha, come potete aspettare, scritto molte volte su finanze e microeconomica.
E' davvero un piacere per me di invitarlo al centro di Bologna
e di portare il podium a lui, al Prof. Draghi.
Sottotitoli e revisione a cura di QTSS
Before I start with the formal part of my lecture,
let me say just one or two words about how our friendship started and developed.
You recall, actually, when Giorgio and Paolo called him to Rome in the early 80s.
I think it must have been 81, 82.
And that was my first contact with him.
And frankly, it's a contact I never forgot because it sent a very clear message.
He was there to rate projects according to benefits and costs.
And then he was asked to rate projects in a different way
that had nothing to do with economic convenience or profitability
or the basic transparent reason for having that or this project.
He was asked to do so and he refused it.
He refused it and there was a period of time,
which I'm sure Marli remembers very well,
that was not short when he had to go through a very painful experience
with some politicians of the time.
And he was left alone, with the exception of these two friends here.
And he was left alone.
But in spite of this, he didn't give in.
He resisted and in the end he resigned.
So to me that was, I was not in the civil service at that time,
but certainly to me that was a great example of what a civil servant ought to do.
And it stayed with me forever since then.
Then just a year and a half later I became executive director at the World Bank.
And so I joined him in Washington in the very same institution
where he had spent most of his professional life, the World Bank.
But there I wish to remember three, or I could remember many things,
but I wish to remember three dimensions of that experience.
The first is the professional one.
I was coming from a kind of intellectual background,
which really was not the best for the bank.
I knew nothing about development.
And I knew actually nothing about working in a very large organization like the World Bank.
I was a university professor and I used to spend, I see many of my colleagues at the time,
I used to spend most of my days when I was not lecturing on my own,
basically trying to give form to confused ideas I had at that time.
And then all of a sudden I was in a very large organization,
development-oriented and finance-oriented.
And I think Enzo was an invaluable source of advice.
He really took me by hand and led me through the complicated,
complex roots of this very large and extraordinary organization that is the World Bank.
I mean, without him my experience there would have been much less of a satisfaction.
The second dimension is something that Serena and I and Marli remember very well.
It was our dinners with the children at home, at their home.
And many days we spent together like families do.
We went together shopping, we went together eating, we did lots of things together.
And that's something that's unforgettable.
The third dimension involves another friend, which was just recalled before by Professor Keller,
Riccardo Faini.
And that's the third angle.
The three of us, we were playing tennis together, we were exchanging ideas, views.
Of course we were not always in agreement,
but it was an exchange which was frank but also human and always in good faith.
I think that's what I want to remember about Enzo and especially the three of his qualities combined.
His profound humanity, his wisdom and his total integrity.
And now, if you're concerned, I move to a more formal part of my lecture.
Enzo was not a neoclassical economist or a Keynesian one, a conservative or a liberal.
What I miss most is Enzo's tendency to challenge intellectual cliché and fads,
which made every conversation with him a learning and eye-opening experience.
He was a truly independent-minded person and scholar, passionate at defending his opinions,
but ready to accept others' points of view, if based on sound economic thinking or empirical research.
He was a strong believer in free trade, but also a firm advocate of market regulation.
He defended the global institutions at the time of the anti-global movement,
but also openly criticized the influence that the main shareholders exert on those institutions.
Enzo held important leadership positions both in academic institutions and international organizations.
As an official or government representative in these organizations,
he always resisted political pressures on the decision-making process,
a factor that made his life difficult on many occasions, but which helped him gain high respect.
He had a distinctive ability to combine research with actual policy-making.
In his own words, the two aspects, theory and economic policy, cannot be distinguished too clearly from each other.
Most of Enzo's life was spent in the US, but he remained passionately attached to his own country,
with which he communicated mainly through his opinion pieces on the Sole 24 Ore.
His last book, Crescita e il sviluppo delle nazioni, was written in Italian in order to enhance also in our country
the reflection on economic development, whose presence or absence has fundamental consequences for humanity.
Enzo Grilli's thinking as an academic was certainly influenced by his unique exposure during his many years at the World Bank
and particularly in the mid-90s to the debate on the evolution of the world trade system
with an increasing number of developing countries.
Enzo was a convinced supporter of multilateral trade liberalization.
This process culminated at the end of 1994 with the conclusion of the Uruguay Round
and the subsequent establishment of the World Trade Organization in 1995.
For the first time, developing countries committed to partly opening their markets and to well-defined international trade rules.
In exchange, they could benefit from more open export markets and a greater possibility to protect their stakes
through the new mechanism of trade dispute settlement.
However, the Uruguay Round Agreement left open a number of unfinished issues.
Large agricultural markets in rich countries are still relatively closed.
International trade rules are costly to abide by for a number of developing countries.
Poor countries need foreign aid to develop their supply capabilities and engage successfully in international trade.
The Doha Round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations, which was launched in 2001, was partly devoted to address these issues.
Yet, negotiations have been stalemated for a long time.
As stressed with foresight by Enzo, the failure to conclude the Round poses dangers, particularly in two respects.
Firstly, by inducing as a defensive response a more widespread pursuit of bilateral and regional trade agreements,
that it could result in a loss of bargaining power of the weakest and poorest countries.
Secondly, a failure could threaten the very process of rebalancing of the global economy in which the international community is engaged.
Enzo firmly believed that international trade, by contributing to economic development,
could significantly reduce poverty by fostering specialization in national production of goods according to countries' comparative advantages,
and by increasing knowledge that would help less developed countries to overcome their significant technological gaps.
Enzo stressed particularly two facts.
At the global level, greater efficiency of production raises the return on capital.
At the national level, trading capital-intensive commodities tends to equalize the domestic and global return to capital.
Both effects stimulate investment, which is an extremely powerful engine of growth.
The spectacular performance of export-oriented economies, mainly in East Asia, is a good example of how trade can unleash economic development.
The importance of trade was confirmed during the recent crisis.
World trade collapsed in 2009 as a consequence of the recession, then recovered to pre-crisis levels, and is poised to revert strong trends.
World economic integration is continuing.
Emerging and developing countries have become engines of growth for the economy of the world.
According to World Bank's estimates, about 60% of the increase in world trade in the recovery has been brought about by the rapidly growing demand from emerging countries,
especially for capital goods and consumer durables.
The surge of those exports has been an important contributor to the recovery in high-income countries, in particular in Germany.
In order to help transform the aftermath of the crisis into an opportunity, it is necessary to proceed now more than ever to the structural reforms already envisaged by Enzo in a number of articles.
Reforms capable of enhancing high and sustainable growth rates in developed as well as in developing countries,
which may also be conducive to rebalancing domestic absorption in deficit and surplus countries, most notably in US and China.
He emphasized the accumulation of human capital, education and research and development as essential elements to raise countries' productivity and to drive endogenous technological change.
In his analysis, Enzo devoted much attention to China.
To sustain high growth rates, China should move, he argued, on to a new development phase where accumulation of human capital would outpace that of physical capital.
In the process, a desirable rebalancing of the supply side of the economy from manufacturing to services would be coupled with a parallel development on the demand side,
that is to say, a rise in workers' incomes and in public and private consumption.
As you can see, these are the themes that are being discussed today, that were discussed by the G20 meeting two days ago in Paris.
Enzo was also a passionate communicator.
Whether in an international financial institutions boardroom or in a classroom, he liked to establish a dialectic exchange with his interlocutors.
It was only natural for him to extend his audience through a regular collaboration with the main Italian newspapers and since 2002 as a regular contributor to Il Sole 24 Ore.
For over a decade, he engaged in a dialogue with the public opinion, a fact that, following the example of Luigi Einaudi, was only common to a handful of Italian policymakers and academics.
The world dialogue truly characterizes his newspaper's contributions, both for their frequency, almost monthly in his later years,
and for their structure, a series of short questions and longer answers that is mindful of Socratic conversations.
The occasional reader was always provided with a key that helped him to understand, in a plain language, the essence of the often complex technical and political issues being debated
in international fora.
What were the dominant themes of these conversations?
Perhaps oversimplifying, I would select three subjects which stand out both for their recurrent nature and for their relevance today.
The first subject raised in his commentaries to the G7 meetings or other important international gatherings was the issue of coordination of economic policy decisions by major global players.
Here he was often concerned with the inadequate or delayed European response to global challenges that often left the United States as the dominant or the only player.
For example, at the time of China's negotiations for admission into the WTO, he complained for Europe's notable silence or absence at the negotiating table.
Similarly, he was concerned with Japan's protracted stagnation, which he attributed to the disconnected politics from economics in that country, with the result of silencing another important player.
A second item of Enzo's articles was debt management at times of economic crisis, where he suggested greater market involvement in sovereign debt restructuring through those very same collective action clauses that are now being considered for future euro-area sovereign debt issues.
Similarly, he took strong positions regarding the debt relief proposal for highly indebted emerging countries, launched by then-UK Chancellor of the Czech Republic, Gordon Brown, and approved by the G7 and by the IFIs.
His view was that the accumulation of an unsustainable debt is in most cases the result of a wrong policy stance, and that debt relief should therefore not be granted if the country had not taken a firm commitment to reverse this stance.
A third recurrent subject of Enzo's articles, not surprisingly, was the international financial institutions themselves, their effectiveness and their governance.
He defended the IMF policies during and after the Asian crisis, at the time when the IMF was under heavy attack due to its crisis management strategies on the fiscal and on the monetary front.
He claimed that in a world of free capital flows, the IMF required a new mandate to be able to effectively pursue crisis prevention and management.
Such a mandate should encompass new information requirements, additional monitoring powers, as well as access to a broader volume of resources.
All these issues are still at the top of the IMF reform agenda.
No matter how passionate his defense of IFIs was, Enzo considered IFIs criticisms a normal and even a positive fact because of the IFIs own mandate to pursue public goods with public money.
In fact, Enzo was himself often on the critics bench as when he vividly criticized the World Bank for lending to middle income countries without proof that these loans would achieve better and more effective, that is to say additional, development results than commercial loans.
For those familiar with the aid debate, Enzo's point was nearly called for the certification of additionality of aid money.
To the international financial institutions governance, Enzo devoted a paper jointly written with another friend, Riccardo.
The question raised by the paper's title, who runs the IFIs, was addressed with straightforward intellectual honesty, asking the data to reveal whether IFIs lending was aligned with the financial and commercial interests of their most influential shareholders.
The empirical evidence showed that the US influence was pervasive, while Europe appeared to limit its influence to its trading partners and Japan to Asian countries.
Despite the unequal distribution of power, coalitions were nevertheless necessary to run both IFIs.
He and Riccardo really foresaw the debate on the reform of the IFIs.
Shouldn't developing countries' voting power be better aligned with their economic weight?
Should the objective of greater weight be pursued by promoting regional initiatives such as the proposal of the Asian Monetary Fund?
Could new broader groups such as the G20 provide a better coordination?
After the crisis, there is a growing need of coordination of economic policies in order to reduce instability and uncertainty.
Several international fora can coexist and usefully complement each other.
The G20, even though it has no universal membership, has been particularly effective on a broad set of policy issues, even before they are submitted for discussion.
They are submitted for discussion to the boards of the international financial institutions.
Recent experience in Europe has also shown how regional institutions like the ESF, the European Stabilisation Fund, can usefully collaborate with the IMF and can greatly leverage the IMF funds.
These few thoughts about the life and work of Enzo Grilli bear witness of his eclectic approach to the discipline of economics as well as of his intellectual and moral integrity.
He once claimed that economic growth, which is an essential condition for development, is not a mysterious process.
Of course, this doesn't mean to say that it's mechanical.
In fact, he remarked that understanding its diffusion represents maybe the most important challenge still open.
This calls for a firm commitment to continue the work that he pursued for a whole life.
The ultimate goal is human progress, better quality of life, the chance to free ourselves from the fatal tyranny of ignorance and from the chains of poverty.
Professor Draghi is on a very tight schedule. He has to catch a train back to Rome very soon, but he has said that he'd be happy to entertain a few questions.
We have rules at Johns Hopkins, and one of them is that the highest rank belongs to students in Johns Hopkins.
Therefore, we limit questions to those among our students, and the rest of us can benefit from that, John.
The word, of course, you know to identify yourself and your country.
My name is John Ulrich. I'm from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States.
Thank you so much for your presentation. I know it's very stimulating to the students here.
My question involves something that you said Professor Grille studied.
He talked about how export-related trade helped developing countries like Asia achieve higher standards of living,
and also he talked about how trade and exports helped Germany come out of the recent financial crisis.
This also contributes to macroeconomic imbalances in the world,
and I was wondering in what way should central bankers or policy makers deal with these macroeconomic imbalances,
because in a lot of ways they also contribute to financial crises. Thank you.
Can I, I'll take questions one by one, or?
Why don't we start with this, which is a big question.
When we talk about central bankers, we've got to distinguish different central banks, because they have different mandate.
The ECB, the European Central Bank, has the mandate to ensure price stability.
So the best contribution central bankers can do in Europe, the ECB, is to continue assuring price stability,
and what we call the anchoring of inflation expectation.
We shouldn't forget, I mean you said the central banks contributed to the crisis.
In fact, what happened was that, at least as far as the ECB is concerned,
inflation expectations remained solidly anchored all throughout the crisis,
and that gave the possibility to the ECB to react in a speedy, probably it was the fastest bank to react to the crisis,
and in the most flexible way, it really used a range of instruments and tools that were unprecedented.
In so doing, it could be documented really that the impact of the crisis had been reduced by the proper monetary policy action that was undertaken.
On the broader issue that you raised at the end of your question, when you said the central banks have contributed to the crisis,
I guess you probably must have referred to one of the considerations people make.
What are the origins of the crisis?
Some people say they are macro monetary, in other words, two expansionary monetary policies, especially in other jurisdictions.
Others say that it really had to do with major regulatory flows in the main jurisdictions.
When I say main jurisdictions, I mean in the countries where the major financial centers reside.
Probably the two factors are intertwined. It really depends what job you have.
If you are a central banker, you tend to think that it's regulatory flows, but if you are a regulator, you tend to say that it was monetary policy that was wrong.
Now, being both, I can't really choose which one.
But if I have to express a view, I think regulatory flows really share most of the blame.
It's quite clear that in the three years before the eruption of the crisis, starting in 2004 onward, regulation was deliberately dismantled.
And some of the factors that originated the crisis were possible because that regulation had been dismantled.
Certainly some sort of macro, let me put it this way, abundance of liquidity and savings was also a fertile ground for that.
But I wouldn't argue that that was the originating factor.
Thank you. We're joined, I think, by some of our colleagues in Washington, some students there, although today is a holiday in Washington, in the United States, President's Day, whatever that is.
But in any event, well, we used to celebrate Washington's birthday and Lincoln's birthday, and we were more specific, and now we've aggregated them into a neutral President's Day.
That's an aside that has nothing to do with your talk, Professor Draghi.
But are there any students in Washington with a question?
I'm sorry?
Okay.
Fantastic.
Thank you. I recognize that student.
Is there, yes, another here.
Thank you. My name is Jerome Ingenhoff and I'm from Germany.
Professor Draghi, thanks very much for your talk.
Since we've just been talking about inflation, especially in Europe and the ECB's mandate to deal with inflationary pressure,
what would you say, or how would you say, should the European Central Bank deal with the upcoming challenge that we observe different kinds of inflationary pressures in different eurozone economies?
For example, Germany, where fears of inflation are currently a rise, whereas inflation in other European countries, in other eurozone countries, might be regarded as a helpful thing at the moment.
How would you suggest the ECB deal with it?
I'm sorry, might be regarded as?
Might be regarded as something that is actually beneficial for some of those countries.
Well, I think the answer is actually pretty straightforward.
The monetary policy should assure price stability everywhere.
And the idea that price stability could help the stronger countries and not help the poor or the less dynamic countries doesn't have any justification.
And it's never been as true what I just said as it is today.
Consider that today the greatest obstacle to recovery of investment is not the interest rate, as we all know.
Policy rates have never been so low.
And even credit rates. It's the risk premium.
That is what makes the difference. And that's what is different in different countries.
Now, if you anchor inflation expectations, that's the best thing you can do to reduce risk premium and stabilize them.
Of course you have then other sources of other factors that make risk premium higher here and there.
But, I mean, inflation is certainly a common factor where central banks can be active about.
Other questions?
While students are thinking about those, Professor Droghik, do you want to comment on the role that political speeches had in determining this crisis and changing expectations in a way that might have hurt the ultimate recovery and accelerated the problem?
Essentially the difference between what the financial wizards, the financial predictors might have said and what the politicians were saying.
I think, well, this is not an easy question to answer because it has many dimensions.
We're just coming out of a crisis that was extremely expensive for the real economies, for loss of jobs, for young people and for the taxpayer.
And it's clear that our societies cannot accept paying for another crisis like this.
So all countries, Europe certainly, but also other countries, are trying to give themselves a system that could manage crisis in a better way than it did with the last one.
This better management of crisis will involve substantive changes in the way different actors treat themselves.
For example, changes in the way banks' creditors are going to be treated in the future.
This is very complicated and it's very hard to come out immediately with a perfect communication.
So I think it's fairly understandable that there is some confusion at the very beginning in the way these things are being communicated, especially because these ideas are not completely cooked, are not being worked out completely.
So it's unfortunate, but I think it's also unrealistic to expect that such big changes come out in the public already.