Sottotitoli creati dalla comunità Amara.org
Mr. President, since the birth of the United Nations more than 50 years ago, Italy has played a leading role in strengthening international cooperation for development, addressing conflicts and peace building.
Your country has recognized the importance of agriculture and rural development in these efforts,
and your role as host country to the three concerned UN agencies has been of great importance in strengthening cooperation in this vital area.
Your own long experience of economic issues and your commitment to development and eradicating poverty makes your presence here today especially welcome.
We look greatly forward to your address.
Mr. Secretary General, the world faces critical challenges at the present moment, challenges of war and peace.
All of us here are aware of the burden and responsibility that you personally bear at this difficult time.
We are therefore particularly appreciative that you have been able to be here with us today.
Your presence underlines that even as we face urgent issues of famines and of conflict, we must not forget the underlying structural factors.
The United Nations system under your leadership is striving to address acute emergencies and conflicts,
but also giving equal attention to overcoming poverty, deprivation, insecurity and exclusion that so often are the fuel for conflict.
The Millennium Summit, which has taken place during your period in office and to which you made such a large contribution,
has expressed clearly the determination of the international community to eradicate poverty and hunger.
IFAD is proud of its place within the UN family and we have strongly welcomed your efforts to strengthen the system
and make it work in a more effective and in a more collaborative way.
I am also most pleased to extend a warm welcome to the Secretary of State to the Holy See, His Eminence Cardinal Sudano,
who will share with us today the message of His Holiness Pope John Paul II.
The encouragement this organization has received from the Holy See has been unfailing
and has ensured that our proximity is not just a matter of geography, but rather a sharing of the ideals and aims of human dignity.
It is always a great pleasure to have with us our close friends, Jacques Duf, the Director General of FAO,
and Jim Morris, the Executive Director of the World Food Program.
Their presence here at the anniversary session symbolizes the strong and close collaboration among FAO, WFP, and IFAD.
The Millennium Development Goals to eradicate poverty and hunger give us the opportunity to reinforce this collaboration even further.
Finally, allow me to conclude by reiterating to each and every one of you the appreciation of the Fund's Governors for the honor of your presence today.
We very much look forward to your statements.
I now have the privilege and honor to invite His Excellency Carlo A.C.Ciampi, President of the Italian Republic, to address the governing council.
Signor Presidente del Consiglio dei Governatori,
Signor Presidente del Fondo Internazionale per lo Sviluppo Agricolo,
Signor Secretario Generale delle Nazioni Unite,
Signori Governatori,
Signore e Signori,
It is an honor to inaugurate the Council of Governors on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the IFAD,
in the presence of the Secretary General of the United Nations,
of His Excellency the Secretary of State of the Holy See,
and of such a qualified international representative.
I give you a warm greeting, a message of solidarity and encouragement for your work.
Your conclusions will be decisive for the living conditions and dignity of hundreds of millions of human beings.
In the last 20 years, the world population has grown by more than one and a half billion.
Globally, the inhabitants of the planet have increased and human beings, below the minimum subsistence, have decreased.
Hunger and poverty, however, fly in entire regions and populations of the Earth.
They do not die out if growth is not started locally.
In industrialized countries, the plague of the misery of rural retreat has disappeared only when the same campaigns have been carried out economically,
to create income, to trade, to keep their own inhabitants, allowing them better living conditions, health and education.
The IFAD was born to fight rural poverty in the world of urban development.
For 25 years, the Foundation has been standing firm on the road to the goal, especially in favour of the most disadvantaged populations and in the recovery of post-conflict situations.
It has reduced the vulnerability of communities dependent on the territory and improved the conditions of women.
The international conferences held in the last two years, from the G8 in Genoa to Doha to Monterey, at the peak of the food supply in Rome to Johannesburg,
have aroused consensus and sense of urgency, with continuity and obtaining encouraging results.
They have made consistent increases in the development of public aid after a decade of decline.
It is the first step in the right direction, but it is not enough to make further changes.
The real obstacle is how to do more, more quickly and more efficiently.
It is still fresh the mark of the declaration of the millennium,
the one in which we are all solemnly committed to eliminate those who cross the human condition in the world with their devastating effects.
Poverty, hunger, infantile mortality, the breaking of the IDS.
After almost three years, it is time to measure the path completed.
We are making progress, but small progress.
Of this step, we would miss the basilarian goal set for 2015,
to lift at least half of those who still suffer from hunger.
The productive and virtuous processes must now be started with the necessary expeditiveness,
so that they can bear fruit within the set times.
These are the times that are needed to achieve the necessary capacity of growth,
human and financial material in so many parts of the world, that 2015 is tomorrow.
A single orientation connects all the objectives of the millennium declaration,
on the three great guidelines of health, education and food safety.
In pursuing at the same time the rise of the productive capacities,
of the valid human resources and of the lifespan of the campaigns,
the IFAD has anticipated the strategy of the millennium declaration.
Signor Presidente, Signore Signori,
La crescente separazione fra nord e sud del mondo
influenza profondamente l'attuale contesto internazionale.
E' lo spartiacque lungo il quale trovano origine e alimento le più acute crisi contemporanee.
Non vi è oggi il maggior problema internazionale, politico, economico e ambientale,
che non si colleghi con le intense inquietudini dei popoli del sud del mondo.
Stabilità e sicurezza internazionale, fondata sull'ineguaglianza, hanno i piedi d'ergilla.
Hanno bisogno di un sud che trovi la via del progresso,
assumendo le responsabilità del professor Orti e di un nord che si impegna a fondo per sostenerlo su questa via.
Hanno bisogno in primo luogo di un'Africa integrata nei flussi di crescita mondiali
e partecipe dell'avanzamento della democrazia e dei diritti umani.
Hanno bisogno di un'agricoltura che offra benessere, istruzione e dignità di vita,
non mera subsistenza, ai molti che vivendo nelle campagne soffrono ancora la fame.
L'estrema povertà di un quinto dell'umanità è moralmente inaccettabile ed è un pericolo per tutti.
L'indigenza di grandi comunità, la marginalizzazione di interi continenti,
l'esclusione dalla crescita di interi regioni sono incompatibili con il dialogo fra nazioni e culture
e con l'integrazione economica e finanziaria.
Generano un distruttivo attrito con la libera circolazione di capitale e di merci,
pressioni migratorie che le frontiere nazionali non possono arrestare.
Dopo aver superato mezzo secolo di guerra fredda fra est e ovest,
non vogliamo il dramma della contrapposizione fra nord e sud del mondo nel XXI secolo.
Lo sviluppo dei paesi poveri è diventato la priorità di una politica estera lungimirante dei paesi avanzati.
Per l'Italia e per l'Europa il sud è interlocutore non secondo ad alcuno nei fori multilaterali
e nei rapporti diretti costati e istanze regionali.
Le molteprecie sfide alla comunità internazionale, le minacce gravi alla sicurezza e alla stabilità
vanno affrontate senza esitazioni e senza attenuanti per chi si pone al di fuori dell'illegalità.
Ma non saneremo i fermenti di stabilità che prolifero intorno a noi
se non intervenremo per favorire il progresso economico e sociale dei popoli.
Signor Presidente, Signore e Signori,
il Fondo Internazionale per lo Sviluppo Agricolo ha un ruolo essenziale e centrale,
ha la piena fiducia dell'Italia che ne apprezza lo specifico e qualificato ruolo.
Unanime è il riconoscimento che lo sviluppo rurale e la lotta alla sottoalimentazione
sono un passaggio obbligato e incalzante dello sviluppo e della lotta alla povertà.
Le consultazioni per la sesta ricostruzione di capitale hanno ricevuto una positiva accelerazione
dopo il vertice dell'alimentazione dello scorso giugno.
L'aumento di un quinto è un obiettivo realistico.
L'Italia li contribuirà rimanendo in prima fila fra i paesi donatori.
I vostri lavori potranno rispondere concretamente all'attesa di tanti uomini e donne nel mondo.
Oltre 800 milioni, più due terzi della popolazione povera mondiale,
vivono nelle campagne in condizioni di crescente impoverimento e di emarginazione.
Attraverso il piccolo e meglio credito, e in particolare attraverso il credito alle famiglie e alle comunità locali
intimamente legate alla vita del territorio,
si gettano le basi di uno sviluppo durevole fondato sulle attività agricole.